In this video we'll cover a second
problem to whet your appetite for things
to come, namely the problem of sequence
alignment.
So, this is a fundamental problem in
computational genomics.
If you take a class in the subject, it's
very likely to occupy the very first
couple of lectures So in this problem
you're given two strings over an
alphabet, and no prizes for guessing
which is the alphabet we're most likely
to care about.
Typically these strings represent
portions of one or more genomes.
And just as a toy-running example, you
can imagine that the two strings we're
given are AGGGCT and AGGCA.
Note that the 2 input strings do not
necessarily need to be of the same
length.
Informally speaking the goal of the
sequence 1 at problem is to figure out
how similar the 2 input strings are.
Obviously I haven't told you what I mean
by 2 strings being similar.
That's something would develop.
Over the next couple of slides.
Why might you want to solve this problem?
Well there's actually a lot of reasons,
let me just give you two of many
examples.
One would be to conjecture the function
of the regions of a genome that you don't
understand like say the human genome,
from similar regions that exist in
genome's that you do understand or at
least understand better say the mouse
genome.
If you see a string that has a known
function in the well understood genome
and you see something similar in the
poorly understood genome you might
conjecture it has the same or similar
function.
A totally different reason you might want
to compare the genomes of two different
species is to figure out whether one
evolved directly from the other.
And when.
A second totally different reason you
might want to compare the genomes of two
different species is to understand there
evolutionary relationship.
So for example maybe you have three
species A,B, and C and you're wondering,
whether if B evolved from A, and if C
evolved from B, or whether B and C
evolved independently from a common
ancestor A.
And then you might take genome seril-,
similarity as a measure of proximity in
the evolutionary tree.
So having motivated the informal version
of the problem, let's work toward making
it more formal.
In particular, I owe you a discussion of
what I mean by two strings being similar.
[INAUDIBLE] So to develop intuition for
this, let's revisit the two strings that
we introduced on the previous slide
AGGGCT and AGGCA.
Now, if we just sort of eyeball these two
strings, I mean clearly they're not the
same string, but, we somehow feel like
they're more similar than they are
different.
Different.
So where does that intuition come from?
Well one way to make it more precise is
to notice that these two strings can be
nicely aligned in the following sense.
Let's write down the longer string,
AGGGCT.
And I'm going to write the shorter string
under it and I'll insert a gap, a space
to make the two strings have the same
length.
I'm going to put the space where there
seems to be a quote unquote missing g.
And in what sense is this a nice
alignment? Well it's clearly not perfect.
We don't get a character by character
match of the two strings but there's only
two minor flaws.
So on the one hand we did have to insert
Big gap.
And we do have to suffer one mismatch in
the final column.
So this intuition motivates defining
similarity between two strings, with
respect to their highest quality
alignment, their nicest alignment.
So we are getting closer to a formal
problem statement, but it's still
somewhat under-determined.
Specifically we need to make precise why
we might compare, why we might prefer one
alignment over another.
For example, is it better to have three
gaps and no mix-matches Was it better to
have one gap and one mismatch? So for
this video, we're effectively going to
punt on this question.
We're going to assume this problem's
already been solved experimentally, that
it's known and provided as part of the
input, which is more costly gaps and
various types of mismatches.
So here then, is the formal problem
statement.
So in addition to the two strings over A,
C, G, T we are provided as part of the
input a non negative number indicating
the cost we incur in alignment for each
gap that we insert.
Similarly for each possible mismatch of
two characters like for example
mismatching an A and T we're given as
part of the input a corresponding
penalty.
Given this input, the responsibility of a
sequence alignment algorithm is to output
the alignment that minimizes the sum of
the penalties.
Another way to think of this output, the
minimum penalty alignment is we're trying
to find in effect the minimum cost
explanation for how one of these strings
would have turned into the other.
So we can think of a gap as undoing a
deletion that occurred in the past and we
can think of a misbatch as representing a
mutation.
So this minimum possible total penalty.
That is, the value of this optimal
alignment is famous and fundamental
enough to have its own name, namely the
Needleman-Wunsch score.
So, this quantity is named after the two
authors that proposed efficient algorithm
for computing the optimal alignment.
That appeared way back in 1970, in the
Journal of Molecular Biology.
And now, at last, we have a formal
definition for what it means for two
strings to be similar.
It means they have a small NW score, a
score close to zero.
So, for example, if you had, have a data
base with a whole bunch of genome
fragments, according to this you're going
to define the most similar fragment to be
those with the smallest NW score.
So to bring the discussion back squarely
into the land of algorithms, let me point
out that this definition of genome
similarity is intrinsically algorithmic.
This definition would be totally useless,
unless There existed an efficient
algorithm that, given two strings in
these penalties, computes the best
alignment between those two strings.
If you couldn't compute this score you
would never use it as a measure of
similarity.
So this observation puts us under a lot
of pressure to devise an efficient
algorithm for finding the best alignment.
So how are we going to do that? Well we
could always fall back to brute-force
search, where we iterate over all of the
conceivable alignments of the two
strings.
Compute the total penalty of each of
those alignments, and remember the best
one.
Clearly correctness is not going to be an
issue for group brute-force search, it's
correct essentially by definition.
The issue is how long does it take.
So let's ask a simpler question, let's
just thing about how many different
alignments there are, how many
possibilities do we have to try? So if
you're going to create lengths imagine if
I gave you two strings of length 500,
which is a not unreasonable length.
Which of the following English phrases
best describes the number of
possibilities, the number of alignments
given to strings of 500 characters each?
So I realize this is sort of a cheeky
question but I hope you can gather that
what I was looking for was part D.
So you know, so how big are each of these
quantities anyways.
Well in a typical version of this class
you might have about 50,000 students
enrolled or so.
So its somewhere between 10^4 and 10^5.
The number of people on earth is roughly
7 billion, so that's somewhere between
10^9 and 10^10.
The most common estimate I see for known
atoms in the universe is 10^8.
80.
And believe it or not, the number of
possible alignments of two strings of
length 500 is even bigger than that.
So I'll leave it for you to convince
yourself that the number of possibilities
is at least 2^500.
the real number is actually, noticeably
bigger than that.
and because 10 is at most 2^4, we can
lower bound this number by 10^125.
quite a bit bigger than the number of
atoms in the universe.
And, the point, of course, is just that.
It's utterly absurd to envision
implementing brute-force search, even at
a scale of a few hundred characters.
And you know, forgetting about these sort
of astronomical if you will comparisons
even if you had string lengths much
smaller say in the.
The, you know, a dozen or two you'd never
ever run brute-force it's just not going
to work, and a course notice this is not
the kind of problem this [UNKNOWN]
explosion, this doesn't go away if you
wait a little while for Moore's law to
help you.
This is a fundemental limitation that
say; you are never going to compute
alignments of the strings that you care
about.
Unless you have a fast, clever algorithm.
I'm happy to report that you will indeed
learn such a fast and clever algorithm
later on in this course.
Even better, it's just going to be a
straightforward instantiation of a much
more general algorithm design paradigm
that of dynamic programming.