So, in this video, we're gonna take it at
least partway to the next level for the
heap data structure. That is, we'll
discuss some of the implementation
details. I.e., how would you code a, a
heat data structure from scratch? So
remember what the point of a heap is. It's
a container, and it contains objects, and
each of these objects, in addition to
possibly lots of other data, should have
some kind of key. And we should be able to
compare the keys of different objects; you
know, Social Security numbers for
different employers, edge weights for
different edges in a network, or time
stamps on different events, and so on. Now
remember, for any data structure the
number one thing you should remember is
what are the operations that it supports,
i.e., what is the data structure good for.
And also, what is the running time you can
count on of those operations. So something
we promised in a previous video.
[inaudible] Indicate the implementation of
the miss video is these two primary
operations that a heap exports. First of
all, you can insert stuff into it, and it
takes [inaudible] logarithmic in the
number of objects that the heap is
storing. And second of all, you can
extract an object. That has the minimum
key value, and again we're going to allow
duplicates in our, in our heaps, so if
there's multiple objects, then I'll have a
minimum, a common minimum key value, the
heap will return one of those. It's
unspecified, which one. As I mentioned
earlier, you can also dress up heaps with
additional operations, like you can do
batch inserts, and you can do linear time
rather than log in time. You can delete
from the middle of the heap. I'm not gonna
discuss those in the video; I'm just going
to focus on how you'd implement inserts
and extract [inaudible]. If you wanna know
how heaps really work, it's important to
keep in mind simultaneously Two different
views of a heap One, as a tree And one, as
a, array. So we're gonna start on this
slide with the tree view. Conceptually,
this will be useful to explain how the
heap ope rations are implemented. A
conceptual will think of a heap not just
as any old tree, but as a tree that's
rooted. It'll be binary. Meaning that,
each node will have zero, one or two
children nodes And third, it will be as
complete as possible. So let me draw for
your amusement an as complete as possible
binary tree that has nine nodes. So if the
tree had, had only seven nodes it would
have been obvious what, is complete as
possible means. It would have meant we
just would have had three completely
filled in levels. If it had, had fifteen
nodes it would have had four completely
filled in levels. If you're in between,
these two numbers that are powers of two
minus one, well we're going to call a
complete to the tree as just in the bottom
level you fill in the leaves from left to
right. So here the two extra leaves on the
fourth level are both, pushed as far to
the left as possible. So, in our minds,
this is how we visualize heaps. Let me
next define the heat property. This
imposes an ordering on how the different
objects are arranged in this tree
structure. The heap property dictates that
at every single node of this tree it
doesn't matter if it's the root if it's a
leaf if it's an internal node whatever. At
every node X the key of the object stored
in X should be no more than the keys of Xs
children. Now X may have zero children if
it's a leaf it may have one child or it
may have two children whatever those cases
zero one or two children all those
children keys should be at least that of
key at X. For example, here is a heap with
seven nodes. Notice that I am allowing
duplicates. There are three different
objects that have the key value four, in
this heap. Another thing to realize is
that while the heap property imposes
useful structure on how the objects can be
arranged it in no way uniquely pins down
their structure. So this exact same set of
seven keys could be arranged differently
and it would still be a heap. The
important thing is that, in any heap, the
root has to have a minimum value key. Just
like in the se two organizations of these
seven keys, the root is always a four, the
minimum key value. So that's a good sign,
given that one of the main operations
we're supposed to. Quickly implement, is
to extract the minimum value. So at least
we know where it's going to be, it' gonna
be at the root of a heap. So while in or
minds we think of heaps as organized in a
tree fashion, we don't literally implement
them as trees. So in something like search
trees, you actually have pointers at each
node and you can traverse pointers to go
from a [inaudible] to the children from
the children to the parents, yada, yada,
yada. Turns out it's much more efficient
in a heap to just directly implement it as
an array. Let me show you by example how a
tree like we had on the last slide maps
naturally onto an array representation. So
let's look at a slightly bigger heap, one
that has nine elements. So let me draw an
array with nine positions. Labeled one,
two, three all the way up to nine And the
way we're going to map this tree which is
in our mind to this array implementation
is really very natural. We're just going
to group the nodes of this tree by their
level. So, the root is gonna be the only
node at level zero. Then the children of
the roots are level one, their children
constitute level two, and then we have a
partial level three, which is just these
last two notes here. And now we just stick
these notes into the array, one level at a
time. So the roots winds up in the
privileged first position, so that's going
to be the, the first, the object which is
the first copy of the four. Then we put in
the level one object, so that's the second
copy of the four and the eight, and then
we put in level two Which has our third
four along with the two nines. And then we
have the last two notes from level three
rounding out the penultimate and final
position of the array. And you might be
wondering how it is we seem to be having
our cake and eating it, too. On the one
hand we have this nice, logical tree
structure. On the other hand we have this
array implementation and we're not wasting
any space on the usual pointers you would
have in a tree to traverse between parents
and children. So where's the free lunch
coming from? Well the reason is that
because we're able to keep this binary
tree as balanced as possible, we don't
actually need pointers to figure out who
is whose parent and who is whose child. We
can just read that off directly From the
positions in the array. So, let me be a
little bit more specific. If you have a
node in the fifth position, I'm assuming I
here is not one, right? So the, the root
doesn't have any, does not have a parent
But any other, any other objects in
position I does have a parent And what the
position that is, depends on, in a simple
way on whether I is even or odd. So if I
is even, then the parent is just
[inaudible] the position of I/2, and if I
is odd, then it's going to be I/2. Okay,
that's a fraction. So we take the floor
that is we round down to the nearest
integer. If I is odd, So for example, the
objects in positions two and three have as
their parent the object in position one,
and those in four and five have the one in
position two as his parent. Six and seven
have as their parents the node in, the
object in position three and so on And of
course we can invert this function we can
equally easily determine who the children
are of a given node so if we have an
object in position I. Then you notice that
the children of I are gonna be at the
position 2i and 2i+1. Of course those may
be empty so if you have a leaf of course
that doesn't have any children and then
maybe one node that has only one child.
But in the common case of an internal node
it's gonna be two children that are gonna
be in positions 2i and 2i+1. So rather
than traversing pointers it's very easy to
just go from a node to its parent to
either one of its children just by doing
these appropriate trivial calculations
with respects to its position. So this
slide illustrates, some of the. Lower
level reasons that heaps are quite a
popular data struct ure So the first one,
just in terms of storage. We don't need
any overhead at all. We are just. We have
these objects; we're storing them directly
In an array, with no extra space. Second
of all, not only do we not have to have a
space for pointers But we don't even have
to do any traversing. All we do are these
really simple. Divide by two or multiply
two operations And using bit shifting
tricks. Those can also be implemented
extremely quickly. So, the next two slides
let me indicate, at a high level, how you
would implement the two exported
operations, namely insertion and extract
[inaudible] in time algorithmic in the
size of the heap And rather than give you
any pseudo code, I'm just going to show
you how these work by example. I think it
will be obvious how they extended the
general case. I think just based on this
discussion, you'll be able to code up your
own versions, of insert and extract
[inaudible], if you so desire. So let's
redraw the 9-node heap that we had on the
previous slide and again, I'm gonna keep
drawing it as a tree and I'm gonna keep
talking about it as a tree but always keep
in mind the way it's really implemented is
in terms of these array and when I talk
about the parent of a node, again, what
that means is you go to the appropriate
position given the position of the node
from where you started. So let's suppose
we have an existing heap, like this blue
heap here And we're called upon to insert
a new object. Let's say with a key value
K. Now remember heaps are always suppose
to be perfectly balanced binary trees. So
if we want to maintain the property that
this tree is perfectly balanced is pretty
only one place we can try to put the new
key K and that's as the next leaf. That is
it's going to be the new right most leaf
on the bottom level. Or in terms of the
array implementation we just stick it in
the first non empty slot in the array And
if we keep track of the array size we're
getting constant time of course know where
to put the new key. Now whether or not we
can get away with this depends on what the
actual key value K is But, you know, for
starters we can say, what if we insert a
key that's seven? Well, then we get to
say, whew, we're done. So, the reason
we're done is cuz we have not violated the
heap property. It is still the case that
every node has key no bigger than that of
its children. In particular, this third
copy of a four, it picked up a new child,
but its key seven was bigger than its key
four. So, you can imagine that maybe we
get lucky with another insert. Maybe the
next insertion is a ten And again, we put
that in the next available spot in the
last level And that becomes the second
child of the third copy of the four And
again we have no violation of the heap
property. No worries still got a heap And
in these lucky events insertion is even
taking constant time. Really all we're
doing is putting elements at the end of an
array and not doing any rearranging. So
where it gets interesting is when we do an
insertion that violates the heap property.
So let's supposed we do yet another
insertion, and the left child of this
twelve, it becomes a five. Now we got a
problem. So now we have a as perfectly as
possible balanced binary tree, but the key
property is not satisfied. In particular,
it's violated at the node twelve. It has
one child. The key of that child is less
than its own key. That's no good. So is
there some way we can restore the heap
property? Well, a natural idea is just to
swap the positions of the five and the
twelve, and that's something that of
course can be done in constant time, cuz
again from a node, we can go to the parent
or the child in constant time just with a
suitable trivial computation. So we say
okay, for starters we put the five at the
end, but that's no good. So we're gonna
swap the five with the twelve And now we
see we're not out of the woods. No longer
is there a heap violation at the node
twelve. That's been fixed. We've made it a
leaf But we've Pushed up the heap
violations. So now instead it's the eight
that has a problem. The eight used to h
ave two children, with keys twelve and
nine that was fine. Now the eight has two
children with keys five and nine. The five
is less than the eight, that's a violation
of the heap property But again, that's the
only violation of the heap property.
There's no other node you could have
screwed up, because eight was the only
person whose children we messed around
with. Alright So now we just it again.
Let's try [inaudible] again, locally fix
the heap violation by swapping the five
with the 8s And now we see we've restored
order. The only place where there could
possibly be a violation of the heap
property is at the root. The root, when we
did this swap, the only person whose
children we really messed with was the
root four, and fortunately its new child
has key five, which is bigger than it. One
subtle point that you might be thinking
that in addition to screwing up at the
root node, that messing around with his
children, maybe we could have screwed up
the twill by messing around with its
parent. Alright, its parent used to be
five, and now its parent is eight. So is
there some possibility that his parent
would all of a sudden have a key bigger
than it But if you think about it, this
eight and this twelve, they were a
parent-child relationship in the original
heap Right? So back in the blue heap, the
twelve was under the 8s. Now the twelve is
under the eight yet again. Since we have
the heap property for that pair before, we
certainly have it now. So in general, as
you push up this five up the tree, there's
only going to be one possible edge that
could be out of order And that's between
where the five currently resides and
whatever its parent is. So when the 5's
parent was twelve that was a violation
When 5's parent was eight that was a
violation But now that we've pushed it up
two levels and 5's parents is four, that's
not a violation because four is less than
five. So in general, step two of insertion
is, you do this swap, which it's called a
lot of different things. I'm gonna call it
bubble up because that's how I learned it
more years ago than I care to admit But
also this is called, sometimes sift up,
happily up, and so on. So now told you to
just how to implement insertions by
repeated bubbling ups in a heap data
structure And this is really how it works,
there is nothing I haven't told you but
you know, I'm not going to really fill in
all the details but I'll encourage you to
do that on your own time, if it's
something that interests you And the two
main things that you should check is first
of all, is bubbling up process is gonna
stop and when it stops, it stops with the
heap property restored. The second thing
needs to be checked in this, I think is
easier to see is that we do have the
desire one time log [inaudible] make in
the number of elements in the heap. The
key observations areas that because this
is a perfectly balanced binary tree. We
know exactly how many levels there are. So
this is basically log based two event
levels where n is the number of items in
the heap And what is the running time of
this insertion procedure while you only do
a constant amount of work at each level,
just doing the swap and comparison and
then in the worst case, you'll have to
swap at every single level and there is a
lot [inaudible] number of levels. So
that's insertion. Let's now talk about how
do we implement the extract [inaudible]
operation and again I'm gonna do this by
example and it's gonna be by repeating the
[inaudible] of a bubble [inaudible]
procedure. So the Extract main operation
is responsible for removing from the heap
an object with minimum key value and
handing it back to the client on a silver
platter. So it pretty much have to whip
out the root. Remember the minimum is
guaranteed to be at the root. So that's
how we have to begin to extract the
subroutine is just we pluck out the root
and hand it back to the client. So this
removal of course leaves a gaping hole in
our tree structure and that's no good. One
of the [inaudible] responsible for
maintaining is that we always have an as
perfectly balanced as possib le binary
tree And if you are missing a root you
certainly don't have an almost perfect.
Binary tree So, what are we going to do
about it? How do we fill this hole? Well,
there's pretty much only one node that
could fill this hole without causing other
problems with the tree structure, and that
is the very last node. So the rightmost
leaf at the bottom level one that simple
fix is to swap that up and have that take
the place of the original root. So in this
case, the thirteen is going to get a
massive promotion And get teleported all
the way to be the new root of this tree.
So now we've resolved our structural
challenges. We now again have a, as
perfectly balanced as possible, binary
tree But of course now we've totally
screwed up the heap property, right. So
the heap property says that at every node,
including the root, the key value at that
node has to be less than both of the
children, and now it's all messed up.
Right, so at the root, the key value's
actually bigger than both of the children.
And matters that are little bit more
tricky than they were with insertion,
right, when we inserted at the bottom
because every note has a unique parent. If
you wanna push a note upward in the tree,
there's sort of only one place you can go,
right, all you can do is swap with your
parent, unless you're going to try to do
something really crazy But if you want to
do something local, pretty much you only
have a unique parent you got to swap with.
Now when you're trying to push notes down
to the rightful position in the tree,
there is two different swaps you could do,
one for the left child, one for the right
child and the decision that we make
matters To see that concretely, let's
think about this example. There's this
thirteen at the root, which is totally not
where it should be, and there's the two
children. The four and the eight, and we
could try swapping it with either one. So
suppose we swap it in a misguided way with
the right child, with the eight. So now
the eight becomes the root, and the
thirteen gets pushed dow n a level. So on
the one hand; we made some progress
because now at least we don't have a
violation between the thirteen and the
eight. On the other hand, we still have
violations involving the thirteen. The
thirteen is still violated with respect to
the twelve and nine And moreover, we've
created a new problem between the eight
and the four, right? So now that the eight
is the root, that's still bigger than its
left child, this four. So it's not even
clear we made any progress at all when we
swapped the thirteen with the eight, okay?
So that was a bad idea And if you think
about it would made it a bad idea, the
stupid thing was to swap it with the
larger child. That doesn't make any sense.
We really want to swap it with the smaller
child. Remember, every node should have a
key bigger than both of its children. So
if we're going to swap up either the four
or the eight, one of those is going to
become the parent of the other. The parent
is supposed to be smaller, so evidently we
should take the smaller of the two
children and swap the thirteen with that.
So we should swap the thirteen with the
figure. Not with E And now we observe a
phenomenon very much analogous to what we
saw in insert. When we were bubbling up
during insertion, it wasn't necessarily
that we fixed violations of the heat
property right away But we would fix one
And then introduce another one that was
higher up in the tree And we had
confidence that eventually we could just,
push this violation up to the root of the
tree And squash it, just like we're trying
to win a game Of Whack a Mole. Here, it's
the opposite. It's just in the opposite
direction. So we swap the thirteen with
the four. It's true we've created one new
violation of the heap property. That's
again involving the thirteen with its
children nine and four. But we haven't
created any new ones. We've pushed the
heap violation further down the tree And
hopefully again, like in Whack a Mole.
We'll squash it At the bottom. So after
swapping the thirteen and the four, now we
just gotta do t he same thing. We say,
okay, we're not done. We still don't have
a heap. This thirteen is bigger than both
of its children But now, with our
accumulated wisdom, we know we should
definitely swap the thirteen with the
four. We're not gonna try swapping with
the nine, that's for sure. So we move the
four up here And we, the thirteen takes
the 4's old place. Boom! Now we're done.
So now we have no violations remaining.
The thirteen in its new position has no
children so there's no way it can have any
violations, and the four because it was
the smaller child that's gonna be bigger
than the 9's so we haven't introduced a
huge violation there, and again we have
these consecutive 4's but we know that's
not gonna be a problem because those were
consecutive 4's in the original heap as
well. So you won't be surprised to hear
that this procedure by which you push
something down, by swapping it with its
smaller children, is called bubble down,
and extract men is nothing more than
taking more than, taking this last leaf,
promoting it to the top of the tree, and
bubbling down until the heap violation has
been fixed. So again on a conceptual level
that's all of the ingredients necessary
for a complete from scratch implementation
of extracting the minimum from a heap and
as before, I'll leave it for you to check
the details. So first of all you should
check that in fact this bubble down has to
at some point halt And when it halts you
do have a bona fide heap. The heap
property is definitely restored And second
of all the running time is, is
logarithmic. Here the running time
analysis is exactly the same as before so
we already have observed that the heights
of a heap because it's perfectly balanced
is essentially the log base two of the
number of elements in the heap and in
bubbling down all you do is a constant
amount of work per level. All you have to
do is a couple comparisons and swap. So,
that's a peek at what's under the hood in
the heap data structure. A little bit
about the guts of its elementation. So
after having seen this, I hope you feel
like a little bit more hard-core of a
programmer, a little bit more hard-core of
a computer scientist.