We've arrived at another one of computer
science's greatest hits, namely Dijkstra's
shortest path algorithm. So let me tell
you about the problem. It's a problem
called single source, shortest paths.
Basically what we wanna do is compute
something like driving directions. So
we're given as input a graph, in this
lecture I'm gonna work with directed
graphs, although the same algorithm would
work with undirected graphs with cosmetic
changes. As usual, we'll use m to denote
the number of edges and N to denote the
number of vertices. The input also
includes two extra ingredients. First of
all, for each edge E, we're given, as
input, a non negative length, which I'll
denote by L sub B. In the context of a
driving directions application, L sub B
could denote the, the mileage, how long,
this particular road is, or it could also
denote, the expected travel time along the
edge. The second ingredient is a vertex
from which we are looking for paths. This
is exactly the same as we had in breadth
first search and depth first search. We
have an originating vertex which we'll
call here, the source. Our responsibility
then is to given this input to compute for
every other vertex V in this network the
length of a shortest path from the source
vertex S to that destination vertex V. And
so, just to be clear, what is the length
of a path that has, say, three edges in
it? Well, it's just the sum of the length
of the first edge in the path, plus the
length of the second edge in the path,
plus the length of the third edge in the
path. So if you had a path like this with
three edges, and lengths one, two, and
three, then the length of the path would
just be six. And then we define the
shortest SV path in the natural way. So
amongst all of the paths directed from S
to V each one has its own respective path
length. And then the minimum overall SV
paths is the shortest path distance in the
graph G. So, I'm going to make two
assumptions for these lectures. One is
really just for convenience. The other is
really important. The other assumption
without which Dijkstra's algorithm is not
correct, as we'll see. So, for convenience
we'll assume that there is a directed path
between S and every other vertex V in the
graph. Otherwise the shortest path
distance is something we'd define to be
plus infinity. And the reason this is not
a big assumption is if you think about it,
you could detect which vertices are not
reachable from S just in a pre processing
step using say breadth first or depth first
search and then you could delete the
irrelevant part of the graph  and run
Dijkstra's algorithm as we'll describe it
on what remains. Alternatively Dijkstra's algorithm
will quite naturally figure out which
vertices there are paths to from S and which
ones there are not. So this won't really come up.
So, to keep it simple
just think about, we have an input graph
where you can get to S to V. For every
different vertex V and the challenge then
is amongst all the ways to get from S to V
what is the shortest way to do it? So the
second assumption already appears in the
problem statement, but I want to reiterate
it just so it's really clear. When we
analyze Dijkstra's algorithm, we always
focus on graphs where every length is
non-negative. No negative edge lengths are
allowed. And we'll see why a little bit
later in the, in the video. Now in the
context of a driving directions
application it's natural to ask the
question, why would you ever care about
negative edge lengths. Until we invent a time
machine it doesn't seem like negative edge
lengths are gonna be relevant when you're
computing literal paths through literal
networks. But again remember that paths
can be thought of as more abstractly as a
just sequence of decisions. And some of
the most powerful applications of shortest
paths are coming up with optimal ways such
sequences. So, for example, maybe you're
engaging in financial transactions, and
you have the option of both buying and
selling assets at different times. But if
you sell, then you get some kind of
profit, and that would correspond to a
negative edge length. So there are quite
interesting applications in which
negative edge lengths are relevant. If you
are dealing with such an application,
Dijkstra's algorithm is not the algorithm to
use. There is a different shortest path
algorithm, a couple other ones, but the
most well known one is called Bellman
Ford. That's something based on dynamic
programming, which we may well cover in a
sequel course. Okay, So for Dijkstra's
algorithm we always focus on graphs that
have only non negative edge lengths. So
for the next quiz I just wanna make sure
that you understand the single source
shortest path problem. Okay let me draw
for you here a simple four-node network and
ask you for what are the four shortest
path lengths. So from the source for text S
to each of the four vertices in the network.
Alright, so the answer to this
quiz is the final option, zero, one,
three, six. To see why that's true, well
all of the options had zero as the
shortest path distance from S to itself so
that just seemed kinda obvious. So the
empty path will get you from S to itself
and have zero length. Now suppose you
wanted to get from S to V. Well, there's
actually only one way to do that, you have
to go along this one hop path. So the only
path has length one. So, the shortest path
distance from S to V is one. Now W's more
interesting. There's a direct one hop
path, SW, that has length four. But that
is not the shortest path from S to W. In
fact, the two hop path, that goes through
V as an intermediary, has total path length
three, which is less than the length of
the direct arc from S to W. So therefore,
the shortest path distance from S to W is
going to be three. And finally, for the
vertex T, there's three different paths
going from S to T. There's the T, two hop
path that goes through V. There's the two
hop path which goes through W. Both of
those have path length seven. And then
there's the three hop path which goes
through both V and W, and that actually
has a path length of one plus two plus
three equals six. So despite having the
largest number of edges, the zigzag path
is, in fact, t he shortest path from S to
T, and it has length six. Alright. So
before I tell you how Dijkstra's algorithm
works, I feel like I should justify the
existence of this video a little bit.
Alright, Because this is not the first
time we've seen shortest paths. You might
be thinking, rightfully so. We already
know how to compute shortest paths. That
was one of the applications of breadth
first search. So the answer to this
question is both yes and no. Breadth first
search does indeed compute shortest paths.
We had an entire video about that. But it
works only in the special case where the
length of every edge of the graph is one.
At the moment we're trying to solve a more
general problem. We're trying to solve
shortest paths when edges can have
arbitrary non negative edge lengths. So for
example, in the graph that we'd explored
in the previous quiz, if we ran
breadth-first search, starting from the
vertex S, it would say that the shortest
path distance from S to T is two. And
that's because there's a path with two
hops going from S to T, put differently, T
is in the second layer emanating from S.
But as we saw in the quiz, there is not in
fact a shortest two hop path from S to T
if you care about the edge lengths,
rather, the minimum length path, the
shortest path, with respect to the edge
weights, is this three hop path, Which has
a total length of six. So breadth first
search is not going to give us what we
want, when the edge lengths are not all
the same. And if you think about an
application like driving directions, then
needless to say, it's not the case that
every edge in the network is the same.
Some roads are much longer than others,
some roads will have much larger travel
times than others; so we really do need to
solve this more general shortest path
problem. Similarly if you're thinking more
abstractly about a sequence of decisions
like financial transactions, in general,
different transactions will have different
values; so you really want to solve
general shortest paths not in the special
case that breadth first search solves. Now
if you're feeling particularly sharp
today, you might have the following
objection to what I've just said. You
might say, yeah, big deal. General edge
weights, unit edge weights. It's basically
the same. Say you have an edge that has
length three. How is that fundamentally
different than having a path with three
edges, each of which has length one? So
why not just replace all the edges with a
path of edges of the appropriate length?
Now we have a network in which every edge
has unit length and now we can just run
breadth first search. So, put succinctly,
isn't it the case that computing shortest
paths with general edge weights reduces to
computing shortest paths with unit edge
weights? Well the first comment I want to
make is I think this will be an excellent
objection to raise. Indeed, as
programmers, as computer scientists this
is the way you should be thinking. If you
see a problem that seems superficially
harder than another one, you always want
to ask. Maybe with a clever trick I can
reduce it to a problem I already know how
to solve. That's a great attitude in
general for problem solving. And indeed if
all of the edge lengths were just small
numbers like 1,2 and 3 and so on, this trick
would work fine. The issue is when you
have a network where the different edges
can have very different lengths. And that's
certainly the case in many applications.
Definitely road networks would be one,
where you have both, sort of, long
highways and you have neighborhood
streets. And potentially, in financial
transaction based networks, you would also
have a wide variance between the value of
different transactions. And the problem
then is, some of these edge lengths might be
really big. They might be a 100. They
might be a 1000. It's very hard to put
a priori bounds on how large these edge
weights could be. So if you start.
wantonly replacing single edges with these
really long paths of length 1,000, you've
blown up the size of your graph way too
much. So you do have a faithful
representation of your old network, but
it's too wasteful. So even though breadth
first search runs in linear time, it's now
on this much larger graph, and we'd much
prefer something which is linear time or
almost linear time that works directly on
the original graph and that is exactly
what Dijkstra's shortest path algorithm is
going to accomplish. Let's now move on to
the pseudocode for Dijkstra's shortest
path algorithm. So this is another one of
those algorithms where no matter how many
times I explain it, it's super fun to
teach. And the main reason is because it
exposes the beauty that pops up in good
algorithm design. So, the pseudo code, as
you'll see in a second, is itself very
elegant. We're just going to have one loop
and then in each iteration of the loop,
we will compute the shortest path distance
to one additional vertex. And by the end
of the loop we'll have completed shortest
path distances to everybody. The proof of
correctness, which we'll do in the next
video, is a little bit subtle but also
quite natural, quite pretty. And then
finally, Dijkstra's algorithm will give
us our first opportunity to see the
interplay between good algorithm design
and good data structure design. So with a
suitable application of the heap data
structure, we'll be able to implement
Dijkstra's algorithm so it runs blazingly
fast, almost linear time. Namely, M times
log N. But I'm getting a little ahead of
myself. Let me actually show you the
pseudo code. At a high level, you really
should think of Dijkstra's algorithm as
being a close cousin of breadth first
search. And indeed, if all of the edge
lengths are equal to one, Dijkstra's
algorithm becomes breadth first search. So
this is sort of a slick generalization of
breadth first search when edges can have
different lengths. So, like our generic
graph search procedures, we're going to
start at the source for a text S. And in
each iteration, we're going to conquer one
new vertex. And we'll do that once each
iteration after N minus one iterations,
we'll be done. And in each iteration,
we'll correctly comp ute the shortest path
distance to one new possible destination
vertex, V. So let me just start by
initializing some notation. So capital X
is going to denote the vertices we've
dealt with so far. And by dealt with I
mean we've correctly computed shortest
path distance from the source vertex to
every vertex in X. We're going to augment
X by one new vertex in each iteration of
the main loop. Remember that we're
responsible for outputting N numbers, one
for each vertex. Were not just computing
one thing we're computing the shortest
path distance from the source vertex S to
every other vertex. So, I'm going to frame
the output in terms of this array capital
A. So for each vertex we're going to have
an entry in this array A and the goal is
at the end of the algorithm, A will
be populated with the correct shortest
path distances. Now to help you understand
Dijkstra's algorithm, I'm gonna do some
additional bookkeeping which you would not
do in a real implementation of Dijkstra's
algorithm. Specifically, in addition to
this array capital A, in which we compute
shortest path distances from the source
vertex to very other destination, there's
gonna be an array capital B in which we'll
keep track of the actual shortest path
itself, from the source vertex S to each
destination V. So the arrays A and B will
be indexed in the same way. There'll be
one entry for each possible destination
vertex V. Capital A will store just a
number for each destination's shortest path
distance. The array B in each position
will store an actual path, so the path,
the shortest path from S to V. But again,
you would not include this in an actual
implementation. I just find in my
experience it's easier for students to
understand this algorithm if we think of
the paths being carried along as
well. So now that I've told you the
semantics of these two arrays, I hope it's
no surprise how we initialize them for the
source vertex itself S. The shortest path
distance from S to itself is zero, the
empty path gets you from S to S with
length zero, there's no negative edges by
assumption, so there's no way you can get
from S back to S with non positive length,
so this is definitely the shortest path
distance for S. By the same reasoning, the
shortest path from S to S is just the
empty path, the path with no edges in it.
So now let's proceed to the main while
loop. So the plan is we wanna grow this
set capital X like a mold that covers the
entire graph. So in each iteration it's
going to grow and cover up one new vertex
and that vertex will then be processed and
at the time of processing we're
responsible for computing the shortest
path distance from S to this vertex and
also figuring out what the actual shortest
path from S to this vertex is. So in each
iteration we need to grow X by one node to
ensure that we've made progress. So the
obvious question is, which node should we
pick? Which one do we add the X next? So
there's gonna be two ideas here. The first
one we've already seen in terms of all of
these generic graph search procedures,
which is we're going to look at the edges
and vertices which are on the frontier. So
we're going to look at the vertices that
are just one hop away from the vertices
we've already put into X. So that
motivates at a given iteration of the while
loop to look at the stuff we've already
processed that's X. And the stuff we
haven't already processed, that's V minus
X. S of course starts in X and we never
taken anything out of X so S is still
there, you know. And some generic
iteration of the while loop, we might have
some other vertices that are in X. And in
a generic iteration of this while loop,
there might be multiple vertices which are
not in X. And now as we've seen in our
graph search procedures there in general
are edges crossing this cut, so there are
edges which have one end point in each
side, one end point in X and one end point
outside of X. This is a directed graph so
they can cross in two directions, they can
cross from left to right or they can cross
from right to left. So you might have some
edges internal to X. Those are things
we don't care about at this point. You
might have edges which are internal to V
minus X. We don't care about those, at
least not quite yet. And then you have
edges which can cross from X to V minus X.
As well as edges that can cross in the
reverse direction from V minus X back to
X. And the ones we're gonna be interested
in, just like when we did graph search
on directed graphs, are the edges
crossing from left to right. The edges
whose tail is amongst the vertices we've
already seen and whose head is some not
yet explored vertex. So the first idea is
that at each iteration of the while loop
we scan or we examine all of the edges
with tail in X and head outside of X. One
of those is gonna lead us to the vertex
that we pick next. So that's the first
idea, but now we need a second idea,
because this is again quite
under-determined. There could be multiple
vertices, which meet this criterion. So
for example in the cartoon in the bottom
left part of this slide, you'll notice
that there's one vertex here which is
the head of an arc that crosses from left
to right, and there is yet another vertex
down here in V minus X, which again is the
head of an arc that crosses from left to
right. So there are two options, of which
of those two to suck into our set X. And
we might want some guidance about which
one to pick next. So the key idea in
Dijkstra is to give each vertex a score
corresponding to how close that vertex
seems to the source vertex S, and then to
pick among all candidate vertices the one
that has the minimum score. Lemme be more
precise. So among all crossing edges, with
tail on the left side and head on the
right side, we pick the edge that minimizes
the following criterion, the shortest path
distance, that we previously computed from
S to the vertex V, plus the length of the
edge that connects V to W. So this is
quite an important expression, so I will
call this Dijkstra's greedy criterion.
This is a very good idea to use this
method to choose which vertex to add to the
set X, as we'll see. I need to give a name
to this edge which minimizes this quantity
over all crossing edges. So let's call it
V star W star. So for example in the cartoon
in the bottom left maybe of the two edges
crossing from left to right, maybe the top
one is the one that has a smaller value,
of Dijkstra's Greedy Criterion. So in that
case this would be the vertex V star, and
the other end of the edge would be the
vertex W star. So this edge, V star W star
is going to do wonders for us. It will
both guide us to the vertex that we should
add to X next. That's gonna be W star.
It's going to tell us how we should
compute the shortest path distance to W
star as well as what the actual shortest
path from X to W star is. So specifically
in this iteration of the while loop, after
we've chosen this edge V star W star, we
add W star to X. Remember by definition W
star was previously not in capital X. So
we're making progress by adding it to X.
That's one more vertex in X. Now, X is
supposed to represent all of the nodes
we've already processed. So an invariant
of this algorithm is that we've computed
shortest path distances for everybody in X
as well as the actual shortest paths, so
now that we're putting W star in X, we're
responsible for all of this information,
shortest path information. So what we're
gonna do is we're gonna set the, our estimate
of W star's shortest path distance from S
to be equal to the value of this Dijkstra
greedy criterion for this edge. That is,
whatever our previously computed shortest-path
distance from S to V star was, plus the length of
the direct edge from V star to W star. Now
a key point is to realize this code does
make sense, by which I mean, if you think
about this quantity, AV, this has been
previously computed. And that's because
an invariant of this algorithm is we've
always computed shortest path distances to
everything that's in X. And of course, the
same thing holds when we need to assign W
star its shortest path distance because V star
was a member of X, we'd already computed
its shortest path distance so we can
just look up the V star entry position in
the array A. So over on our picture on our
left we would just say, well what did we
compute the shortest path distance to V
star previously? Maybe it's something like
seventeen. And then we'd say you know,
what is the length of this direct edge
from V Star to W Star? Maybe that's six.
Then we would just add seventeen and
six, and we would put 23 as our estimate
of the shortest path distance from S To W
star. So we something analogous with the
shortest paths itself and the array B. That
is again we are responsible since we just
added W star to capital X we're
responsible for suggesting a path from S
to W star in the B array. So what we're
gonna do is we're just going to inherit
the previously computed path to V star and
were just gonna tack on the end one extra
hop, namely the direct edge from V star to W star.
That'll give us a path from S all the way to W
star via V star as an intermediate pit
stop. And that is the entirety of
Dijkstra's algorithm. I have explained all
of the ingredients about how it works at a
conceptual level. So the two things that I
owe you is, you know, why is it correct,
why does it actually compute shortest
paths directly to all the different
vertices, and secondly, how fast can we
implement it. The next two videos are
going to answer both of those questions.
But before we do that, let's go through an example
to get a better feel of how this algorithm
actually works. And I also wanna go
through a non-example so that you can
appreciate how it breaks down when there
are negative edges and that will make it
clear why we do need a proof of
correctness. Because it's not correct
without any assumptions about the edge
lengths.