In this video and the next we are going
to take you to the next level and here
under the hood into implementations of
balanced pioneer research trees.
Now frankly when any great details of all
balance binary research tree
implementations get pretty complicated
and if you really want to understand them
at a fine grain level there is no
substitute for reading an advanced
logarithms textbook that includes
coverage of the topic and/or studying
open source Implementations of these data
structures.
I don't see the point of regurgitating
all of those details here.
What I do see the point in doing, is
giving you the gist of some of the key
ideas in these implementations.
In this first video I want to focus on a
key primitive, that of rotations which is
common to All balanced by the [INAUDIBLE]
of limitations.
Whether is red, black trees, EVL trees, B
or B+ trees, whatever all of them use
rotations.
In the next video we'll talk a little bit
more about the details of red, black
trees in particular.
So, what is the points behind these
magically rotation operations? Well the
goal is to do just constant work, just
re-wire a few pointers, and yet locally
re-balance a search tree, without
violating the search tree properties/g
Property.
So there are two flavors of rotations,
left rotations and right rotations.
In either case, when you invoke a
rotation it's on a parent child pair, in
a search tree.
If it's a right child of the parent, then
you use a left rotation.
We'll discuss that on this slide.
And a right rotation is, in some sense,
an inverse operation which you use when
you have a left child of the parent.
So what's the generic picture look like
when you have a node x in a search tree
and it has some right child y? Well x, in
general, might have some parents.
x might also have some left subtree.
Let's call that left subtree of x, A.
It could, of course, be And then Y has
it's 2 subtrees, lets call the left
subtree of Y B and the right subtree C.
It's going to be very important that
rotations preserve the search tree
property so to see why that's true lets
just be clear on exactly which elements
are bigger then which other elements in
this picture.
So first of all Y being a right child of
X, Y's going to be bigger than x.
Now all of the keys which line the
subtree a because they're to the left of
x these keys are going to be even smaller
than x.
By the same token anything in the subtree
capital c, that's to the right of y so
all that stuff's going to be even bigger
than y.
What about sub tree capital B? What about
the nodes in there? Well, on the one
hand, all of these are in x's right sub
tree, right? To get to any node in B, you
go through x and then you follow the
right child to y.
So that means everything is B is bigger
than x, yet, at the same time, it's all
in the left sub tree of y so these are
all Things smaller than y.
Summarizing all of the nodes in b have
keys strictly in between x and y.
So now that we're clear on how all of
these search keys in the different parts
of this picture relate to each other, I
can describe the point of a left
rotation.
Fundamentally the goal is to invert the
relationship.
Between the nodes x and y.
Currently x is the parent and y is the
child.
We want to rewire a few pointers so that
y is now the parent and x is the child.
Now what's cool is given that is our goal
is pretty much a unique way to put all
these pieces back together to accomplish
it.
So lets just follow our nose.
So remember the goal Y should be the
parent and X should be the child.
Well, X is less then And why and there's
nothing we can do about that.
So if x is going to be a child of y, its
got to the left child.
So your first question might be well what
happened that x is parent.
So x use to have some parent lets call it
p and x's new parent is y.
Similarly y used to have parent x and
there's a question what should y new
parent be? Well y is just going to
inherit x's old parent p.
SO this change has no bearing for the
search tree property.
Either of this collection of nodes was
P's left sub tree, in that case all these
nodes were less than P, or this sub tree
was P's right sub tree which in that case
all of these are bigger than P, but P can
really care less , which of X or Y is
it's direct descendant.
Now lets move on to thinking about
how...what we should do with the
sub-trees A, B and C.
So, we have 3 sub-trees we need to
re-assemble into this picture, and
fortunately we have 3 slots available.
X has both of its child pointers
available and Y has its right child
available.
So what Can we put where? Well, a, is the
sub tree of stuff which is less than both
x and y.
So, that should sensibly be x's left
child.
That's exactly as it was before.
By the same token, capital C is the stuff
bigger than both x and y, so that should
be, y, the bigger nodes child, right
child just as As before.
And what's more interesting is what
happens to subtree capital B.
So B used to be Y's left child but that
can't happen anymore, 'cause now X is Y's
left child.
So, the only hope is to slot capital B
into the only space we have for it, X's
right child.
Fortunately for us this actually works,
sliding B into the only open space we
have for it.
X's right child does indeed preserve the
switch tree property.
Recall we notice that every key in
capital B is strictly between X and Y,
therefore it better be and X's right sub
tree and it better be in Y's right sub
tree, but it is, that's exactly where we
put it.
So that's a left rotation, but if you
understand a left rotation then you
understand a right rotation as well.
because a right rotation is just the
inverse operation.
So that's when you take a parent child
pair, where the child is the left child
of the parent, and now you again want to
invert the relationship.
You want to make the old child the new
parent and the old parent the new child.
And once again given this goal there's
really a unique way to reassemble the
components of this picture so that the
goal's accomplished, so that y is now the
parent of x.
So what are the laudable properties of
rotations? Well first of all I hope it's
clear that they can be implemented.
In a constant time or you were doing a
rewiring a constant number of pointers.
Further more as have discussed they
preserve the search tree property.
So these nice properties are what make
rotations the ubiquitous primitive common
to all balanced search tree
implementations.
So this of course, is not the whole
story.
In a complete specification of a balanced
search tree implementation, you have to
say exactly when and how you deploy these
rotations.
You'll get a small taste of that in the
next video but if you really want to
understand it in more depth, I again
encourage you to check out either a
comprehensive Data structures textbook.
Check out a number of balance search tree
demonstrations, which are readily
available on the web.
Or have a peek at an open source
implementation of one of these data
structures.