Hey, so guess what? We just designed our
first dynamic programming algorithm that
linear time algorithm for computing the
max rate in the penance set in the path
is indeed an extenciation of the general
dynamic programming paradox.
Now defer articulating the general
principle of the paradox home now but I
think they're best understood through
comparate examples now that we have one
to relate them to let me tell you about
these guiding principles, we will in the
coming lectures see many more examples.
Examples.
So, the key that unlocks the potential of
the dynamic programming paradigm for
solving a problem, is to identify a
suitable collection of subproblems.
And these subproblems have to satisfy a
number of properties.
In our algorithm for computing maximum
independent sets in path graphs.
We had n + 1 subproblems.
1 for each prefix of the graph.
So formally, our i-th supbroblem in our
algorithm.
It was to compute the max weight
independence set of g sub i of the path
graph consisting only of the first I
vertices.
So, the first property that you want your
collection of subproblems to possess is
it shouldn't be too big.
It shouldn't have too many different
subproblems.
The reason being is, in the best case
scenario.
You're going to be spending constant
times solving each of those subproblems.
So the number of subproblems is a lower
bound than the running time of your
algorithm.
Now, in the maximum independence set
example, we did great.
We had merely a linear number of
subproblems.
And we did indeed, get away with mere
constant work for each of those
subproblems, giving us our linear running
time bound overall.
The second property you want, and this
one's really the kicker is there should
be a notion of smaller subproblems and
larger subproblems.
In the context of independent sets of
path graphs.
This was really easy to understand.
The subproblems were prefixes of the
original graph and the more vertices you
had the bigger the subproblem.
So in general in dynamic programming you
systematically solve all of the
subproblems.
Beginning with the smallest ones and
moving on to larger and larger
subproblems.
And for this to work it better be the
case that at a given subproblem, given
the solutions to all of the smaller sub
problems, it's easy to infer what the
solution of the current subproblem is.
That is, solutions to previous
subproblems are sufficient to quickly and
correctly compute the solution to the
current subproblem.
The way this relationship between larger
and smaller subproblems is usually
expressed is via recurrence.
And it states what the optimal solution
to a given subproblem is, as a function
of the optimal solutions to smaller
subproblems.
And this is exactly how things played out
in our independence set algorithm.
We did, indeed, have a recurrence.
It just said that the optimal value, the
maximum independent set value for g sub i
was the better of two candidates, and we
justified this using our thought
experiment.
Either you just inherit the maximum
independent set value from the preceding
sub problem, from the i - 1 sub problem,
or you take the optimal solution from two
sub problems back, from Gi - 2 and you
extend it by the current vertex b sub i.
That is, you add the i-th vertices weight
to the weight of the optimal solution
from 2 sub-problems back.
So this is a pattern we're going to see
over and over again.
We'll define sub-problems for various
computational problems and we'll use
recurrence to express how the optimal
solution of a given sub-problem depends
only on the solutions to smaller
sub-problems.
So, just like in our independent set
example, once you have such a recurrence,
it naturally leads to a table filling
algorithm where each entry in your table
corresponds to the optimal solution to 1
sub problem.
And you use your recurrence to just fill
it in, moving from the smaller sub
problems to the larger ones.
So the third property, you probably won't
have to worry about much.
Usually, this just takes care of itself,
but needless to say, after you've done
the work of solving all of your
subproblems, you'd better be able to
answer the original.
Qeustion.
This property's usually automatically
satisfied because in most cases, not all,
but in most cases, the original problem
is simply the biggest of all your
subproblems.
Notice, this is exactly how things worked
in independent sets.
Our biggest subproblem, g sub n was just
the orginal graph.
So once we fill up the whole table Boom.
Waiting for us in the final entry was the
desired solution to the original problem.
So I realize, you know, this is a little
abstract at the moment.
We only have one concrete example to
relate to these abstract concepts.
I encourage you to revisit this again
after we see more examples and we will
see many more examples.
Something all of the forthcoming examples
should make clear is the power and
flexibitlity of the dynamic programming
paradigm.
This is really just a technique that you
have got to know.
Now when you're trying to devise your own
dynamic programming algorithms, the key,
the heart of the matter is to figure out
what the right sub-problems are, if you
nail the sub-problems usually everything
else falls into place in a fairly
formulaic way.
Now if you've got a black belt in dynamic
programming, you might be able to just
stare at a the problem and intuitively
know what the right collection of sub
problems are.
boom, you're off to the races.
But, of course, you know, for white belts
in dynamic programing there's still a lot
of training to be done.
So rather in the forth coming examples
rather than just plucking the sub
problems from the sky We're going to go
through this same kind of process we did
from independent sets and try to figure
out how you would ever come up with these
sub problems in the first place, by
reasoning about the structure of optimal
solutions.
That's a process you should be able to
mimic in your own attempts at applying
this para dine, the problems that come up
in your own projects.
So perhaps you were hoping that once you
saw the ingredients of dynamic
programming all would become clear why on
Earth it's called dynamic programming,
and probably it's not.
So, this is an anachronistic use of the
word programming, it doesn't mean coding.
In the way I'm sure almost all of you
think of it.
it's the same anachronism and phrases
like mathematical or linear programming
it more refers to a planning process.
But you know for the full story let's go
ahead and turn to Richard Bellman himself
he's more or less the inventor of dynamic
programming.
You will see his Bellman-Ford algorithm a
little bit later in the course.
So he answers this question in his
autobiography.
And he say, he talks about when he
invented it, in the 1950s.
And he says those were not good years for
mathematical research.
He was working at a place called RAND.
He says, we had a very interesting
gentlemen in Washington named Wilson
who's the secretary of defense.
and he actually had a pathological fear
and hatred of the word, research.
I'm not using the term lightly, I'm using
it precisely.
His face would suffuse, it would turn
red.
And he would get violent if people used
the term.
Research in his presence.
You can imagine how he felt then about
the term, mathematical.
So The Rand Corporation was employed by
the Air Force.
And the Air Force had Wilson as its boss,
essentially.
Hence, I felt I had to do something to
shield Wilson and the Air Force from the
fact that I was really doing mathematics
inside the Rand Corporation.
What title, what name could I choose? In
the first place, I was interested in
planning and decision making.
But planning, it's not a good word for
various reasons.
I decided therefore to use the word
programming.
Dynamic has a very interesting property
as an adjective in that it's impossible
to use the word dynamic in a pejorative
sense.
Try thinking of some combination that
will possibly give it a pejorative
meaning.
Meaning.
It's impossible.
Thus, I thought Dynamic Programming was a
good name.
It was something not even a congressman
could object to.
So, I used it as an umbrella for my
activity.