In this sequence of lectures we're going
to learn Asymptotic Analysis.
This is the language by which every
serious computer programmer and computer
scientist discusses the high level
performance of computer algorithms.
As such, it's a totally crucial topic.
In this video, the plan is to segue
between the high level discussion you've
already seen in the course introduction
and the mathematical formalism,which
we're going to start developing in the
next video.
Before getting into that mathematical
formalism, however.
I want to make sure that the topic is
well motivated.
That you have solid intuition for what
it's trying to accomplish.
And also that you've seen a couple
simple, intuitive examples.
Let's get started.
[UNKNOWN] analysis provides basic
vocabulary for discussing the design and
analysis in algorithms.
More, it is a mathematical concept it is
by no means math for maths sake.
You will very frequently hear serious
programmers saying that such and such
code runs at O of n time, where such and
such other code runs in o of n square
times.
It's important you know what programmers
mean when they make statements like that.
The reason this vocabulary is so
ubiquitous, is that it identifies a sweet
spot for discussing the high level
performance of algorithms.
What I mean by that is, it is on the one
hand coarse enough to suppress all of the
details that you want to ignore.
Details that depend on the choice of
architecture, the choice of programming
language, the choice of compiler.
And so on.
On the other hand, it's sharp enough to
be useful.
In particular, to make predictive
comparisons between different high level
algorithmic approaches to solving a
common problem.
This is going to be especially true for
large inputs.
And remember as we discussed in some
sense.
Large inputs are the interesting ones.
Those are the ones for which we need
algorithmic enginuity.
For example, asotonic analysis will allow
us to differentiate between better and
worse approaches to sorting.
Better and worse approaches to
multiplying two integers, and so on.
Now most serious programmers if you ask
them, what's the deal with asymptotic
analysis anyways?
They'll tell you reasonably, that the
main point is to suppress both leading
constant factors and lower order terms.
Now as we'll see there's more to
Asymptotic Analysis than just these seven
words here but long term, ten years from
now, if you only remember seven words
about Asymptotic Analysis I'll be
reasonably happy if these are the seven
words that you remember.
So how do we justify adopting a formalism
which essentially by definition
suppresses constant factors and
lower-order terms.
Well lower-order terms basically by
definition become increasingly irrelevant
as you focus on large inputs.
Which as we've argued are the interesting
inputs, the ones where algorithmic
ingenuity is important.
As far as constant factors these are
going to be highly dependent on the
details of the environment, the compiler,
the language and so on.
So, if we want to ignore those details it
makes sense to have a formalism which
doesn't focus unduly on leading constant
factors.
Here's an example.
Remember when we analyzed the merge sort
algorithm?
We gave an upper bound on its running
time that was 6 times n log n plus 6n
where n was the input length, the number
of numbers [COUGH] in the input array.
So, the lower order term here is the 6n.
That's growing more slowly than n log n.
So, we just drop that.
And then the leading constant factor is
the 6 so we supress that well after the 2
supressions we're left with a much
simpler expression N log N.
The terminology would then be to say that
the running time of merge search is big O
of N log N.
So in other words when you say that an
algorithms is big O of some function what
you mean is that after you drop the lower
order terms.
And suppress the leasing, leading
constant factor, you're left with the
function f of n.
Intuitively that is what big O notation
means.
So to be clear I'm certainly not
asserting the constant factors never
matter when you're designing an alg,
analyzing algorithms.
Rather, I'm just saying that when you
think about high-level algorithmic
approaches, when you want to make a
comparison between fundamentally differnt
ways of solving a problem.
Asymptotic Analysis is often the right
tool for giving you guidance about which
one is going to perform better,
especially on reasonably large inputs.
Now, once you've committed to a
particular algorithmic solution to a
problem Of course, you might want to then
work harder to improve the leading
constant factor, perhaps even to improve
the lower order terms.
By all means, if the future of your
start-up depends on how efficiently you
implement some particular set of lines of
code, have at it.
Make it as fast as you can.
In the rest of this video I want to go
through four very simple examples.
In fact, these examples are so simple, if
you have any experience with big O
notation You're probably just better off
skipping the rest of this video and
moving on the mathematical formalism that
we begin in the next video.
But if you've never seen it before I hope
these simple examples will get you
oriented.
So let's begin with a very basic problem,
searching an array for a given integer.
Let's analyze the straight forward
algorithm for this problem where we just
do a linear scan through, through the
array, checking each entry to see if it
is the desired integer t.
That is the code just checks each array
entry in turn.
If it ever finds integer t it returns
true.
If it falls off the end of the array
without finding it it returns false.
So, what do you think?
We haven't formally defined big O
notation but, I've given you an intuitive
description.
What would you say is the running time of
this algorithm as a function of the
length of the array of capital A.
So the answer I am looking for is C, the
O(n) or covalently we would say that the
running time of this algorithm is linear
in the input length n.
Why is that true?
Well, let's think about how many
operations this piece of code is going to
execute.
Actually, the lines of code executed is
going to depend on the input.
It depends on whether or not the target t
is contained in the array a, and if so,
where in the array a it lies.
But, in the worse case, this code will do
an unsuccessful search.
>> T will not be in the array and the
code will scan through the entire array A
and return false.
The number of operations then is a
constant.
There's some initial setup perhaps and
maybe it's an operation to return this
final boolean value, but outside of that
constant which will get suppressed in the
big annotation, it does a constant number
of operations per entry in the array.
And you could argue about what the
constant is, if it's 2, 3, 4 operations
per entry in the array, but the point it
whatever that constant is, 2, 3, or 4, it
gets conveniently suppressed by the Big O
notation.
So as a result, total number of
operations will be linear in n, and so
the Big O notation will just be O of N.
So that was the first example, and the
last three examples, I want to look at
different ways that we could have two
loops.
And in this example, I want to think
about one loop followed by another.
So two loops in sequence.
I want to study almost the same problem
as the previous one.
Where now we're just given two arrays,
capital a and capital b, we'll say both
of the same length n, and we want to know
whether the target t is in either one of
them.
Again, we'll look at the straightforward
algorithm, where we just search through
A, and if we fail to find t in A, we
search through B.
If we don't find t in B either, then we
have to return false.
So the question then is exactly the same
as last time.
Given this new longer piece of code,
what, in big O notation, is its running
time?
Well the question was the same and in
this case the answer was the same so this
algorithm jsut like the last one has
running time big O of N if we actually
count the number of operations it won't
be exactly the ssame as last time it will
be roughly twice as many operations.
As the previous piece of code.
That's because we have to search two
different arrays, each of length n.
So whatever work we did before.
We now do it twice as many times.
Of course, that, too, being a constant
independent of the input length n, is
going to get suppressed once we passed a
big O notation.
So, this, like the previous algorithm, is
a linear time algorithm.
It has running time big O of n.
Let's look at a more interesting example
of two loops where rather than processing
each loop in sequence, they're going to
be nested.
In particular let's look at the problem
of searching whether two given input
arrays each of length n contain a common
number.
The code that we're going to look at for
solving this problem is the most
straightforward one you can, you can
imagine where we just compare all
possibilities.
So for each index i into the array a and
each index j into the array b, we just
see if A i is the same number as B j.
If it is, we return true.
If we exhaust all of the possibilities
without ever finding equal elements Then
we're save in returning false.
The question is of course is, in terms of
big O notation, asymptotic analysis, as a
function of the array length n, what is
the running time of this piece of code?
So this time, the answer has changed.
For this piece of code, the running time
is not big O of n.
But it is big O of n squared.
So we might also call this a quadratic
time algorithm.
because the running time is quadratic in
the input length n.
So this is one of those kinds of
algorithms, where, if you double the
input length.
Then the running time of the algorithm
will go up by a factor of 4, rather than
by a factor of 2 like in the previous two
pieces of code.
So, why is this?
Why does it have [UNKNOWN] running time
[UNKNOWN] of n squared?
Well again, there's some constant setup
cost which gets suppressed in the big
[UNKNOWN].
Again, for each fixed choice of an entry
i into array a, and then index j for
array b for each fixed choice for inj.
We only do a constant number of
operations.
The particular constants are relevant,
because it gets suppressed in the big O
notation.
What's different is that there's a total
of n squared iterations of this double
four loop.
In the first example, we only had n
iterations of a single four loop.
In our second example, because one four
loop completed before the second one
began.
We had only two n iterations overall.
Here for each of the n iterations of the
outer for loop we do n iterations of the
inner for loop.
So that gives us the n times n i.e.
n squared total iterations.
So that's going to be the running time of
this piece of code.
Let's wrap up with one final example.
It will again be nested for loops, but
this time, we're going to be looking for
duplicates in a single array A, rather
than needing to compare two distinct
arrays A and B.
So, here's the piece of code we're going
to analyze for solving this problem, for
detecting whether or not the input array
A has duplicate entries.
There's only 2 small difference relative
to the code we went through on the
previous slide when we had 2 different
arrays the first surprise, the first
change won't surprise you at all which
instead of referencing the array B I
change that B to an A so I just compare
the ith entry of a to the Jth entry of A.
The second change is a little more subtle
which is I changed the inner for loop so
the index J begins.
At I plus 1.
Where I is the current value of the outer
four loops index.
Rather than starting at the index 1.
I could have had it start at the index
one.
That would still be correct.
But, it would be wasteful.
And you should think about why.
If we started the inner four loops index
at 1.
Then this code would actually compare
each distinct pair of elements at a to
each other twice.
Which, of course, is silly.
You only need to compare two different
elements of a to each other one.
To know whether they are equal or not.
So this is the piece of code.
The question is the same as it always is
what in terms of bigger notations in the
input link n is the running time of this
piece of code.
So the answer to this question, same as
the last one.
Big O of n squared.
That is, this piece of code is also a
quad-, has quadratic running time.
So what I hope was clear was that, you
know?
Whatever the running time of this piece
of code is.
It's proportional to the number of
iterations of this double four loop.
Like in all the examples, we do constant
work per iteration.
We don't care about the constant.
It gets suppressed by the big O notation.
So, all we gotta do is figure out how
many iterations there are of this double
four loop.
My claim is that there's roughly n
squared over two iterations of this
double four loop.
There's a couple ways to see that.
Informally, we discussed how the
difference between this code and the
previous one, is that, instead of
counting something twice, we're counting
it once.
So that saves us a factor of two in the
number of iterations.
Of course, this one half factor gets
suppressed by the big O notation anyways.
So the big O, running time doesn't
change.
A different argument would just say, you
know?
How many, there's one iteration for every
distinct choice of i and j of indices
between one and n.
And a simple counting argument.
Says that there's n choose 2 such choices
of distinct i and j, where n choose 2 is
the number n times n minus 1 over 2.
And again, supressing lower-order terms
and the constant factor, we still get a
quadratic dependence on the length of the
input array A.
So that wraps up some of the sort of just
simple basic examples.
I hope this gets you oriented, you have a
strong intuitive sense for what big O
notation is trying to accomplish.
And how it's defined mathematically.
Let's now move onto both the mathematical
developments and some more interesting
algorithms.