So, this set of lectures will be the
final application of the Greedy algorithm
design paradigm.
It's going to be to an application in
compression.
Specifically, I'll show you a Greedy
algorithm for constructing a certain kind
of prefix free binary codes known as
Huffman codes.
So, we're going to spend this video sort
of setting the stage.
So, let's begin by just defining a binary
code.
So, a binary code is just a way to write
down symbols from gen, some general
alphabet in a manner that can computers
can understand that is just a function
mapping each symbol from an alphabet
capital sigma to a binary string, a
sequence of 0's and 1's.
So this alphabet capital sigma could be
any number of things but you know its a
simple example you could imagine its the
letters a through z's in lower case plus
may be the space, character and some
punctuation.
So may be for a set of size 32 overall.
And if you have 32 symbols you need to
encode in binary, well an obvious way to
do it is that happens to be 32 different
binary strings of length 5, so why not
just use one of each of those for your
symbol.
Symbols.
So this would be a fixed length code in
the sense we're using exactly the same
number of bits, namely five to encode
each of the symbols in our alphabet.
This is pretty similar to what's going on
with ASCII codes.
And of course it's a mantra of this class
to ask when can we do better than the
obvious solution.
So in this context, when can we do better
than fixed-length codes.
Sometimes we can in the important case
when some symbols are much more likely to
appear than others.
In that case, we can encode information.
Using fewer bits by deploying variable
length codes.
And this is, in fact, a very practical
idea.
The variable length codes are used all
the time in practice.
One example is in encoding mp3 audio
files.
So if you look at the standard for mp3
encoding, there's this initial phase in
which you do analog to digital conversion
but then once you're in the digital
domain you do apply Huffman codes.
What I'm going to teach you in this video
to compress the length of the files even
further.
And as you know compression, especially
loss less compression like Huffman codes,
is a good thing.
You want to download a file, you want it
to happen as fast as possible or you want
to make file as small as possible.
So a new issue arises when you pass from
fixed length codes to variable length
codes.
So let me illustrate that with a simple
example.
Suppose our alphabet sigma is just four
characters A, B, C, D So the obvious
fixed length encoding of these characters
would just be 00, 01, 10, and 11.
Well suppose we wanted to use fewer bits
and we wanted to use a variable length
encoding.
An obvious idea would be to try to get
away with only 1 bit for a couple of
these characters.
So suppose instead of using a 00 for A
just use a single 0 and instead of using
a double 1 for D we just use a single 1.
So, that's only fewer bits, and it seems
like that can only get getter.
But now, here's the question. Suppose
someone handed you and encoded
transmission consisting of the digits
001.
What would have been the original
sequence of symbols that led to that
encoded version? Alright so the answer is
D,
there is not enough information to know
what 001 was supposed to be an encoding
of.
The reason is, is that having passed to a
variable length encoding there is now
ambiguity.
There is more than one sequence of
original symbols that could of lead under
this encoding to the output 001.
Specifically, answers A and C would both
lead to 001.
The letter A would give you a 0, the
letter B would give you a 01, so that
would give you 001.
On the other hand, AAD would also give
you 001,
so there's no way to know.
Contrast this with fixed length encoding,
if you're given a sequence of bits with a
fixed length code. Of course, you know
where one letter ends and the next one
begins.
For example, if every symbol was encoded
with 5 bits, you would just read 5 bits,
you'd know which symbol it was.
You'd read the next 5 bits, and so on
with variable length codes.
Without further precautions it's unclear
where one symbol starts and the next one
begins.
So that's an additional in issue we have
to make sure we take care of with
variable length codes.
So to solve this problem that with
variable length codes and without further
precautions it's unclear where one symbol
ends and where the next one begins.
We're going to insist that our variable
length codes are prefix free.
So what this means is when we encode a
bunch of symbols we're going to make sure
that for each pair of symbols i and j
from the original alphabet sigma.
The corresponding encoding's will have
the property that neither one is a prefix
of the other.
So going back to the previous slide,
you'll see that that example was not
prefix free.
For example, we used 0 was a prefix of
01.
That led to ambiguity.
Similarly 1, the encoding for D was a
prefix of 10, the encoding for C,
and that also leads to an ambiguity.
So if you don't have prefixes for each
other.
And we'll develop this more shortly.
Then there's no ambiguity.
Then there's a unique way to decode, to
reconstruct what the original sequence of
symbols was given just the zeros and
ones.
So lest you think this is too strong a
property, certainly interesting and
useful variable-length codes exist that
satisfy the prefix-free property.
So one simple example again, just encode
the letters A, B, C, D.
We can get away with encoding the symbol
a, just using a single bit, just using a
zero.
Now, o course to be prefix-free, it
better be the case that our encodings of
b and c and d all start with the bit one.
Otherwise we don't, we're not
prefix-free.
But, we can get away with that so let's
encode a b with one and then an zero.
And now both C and D, better have the
property that they start neither with
zero, nor with 10.
That is they better start with 11, but
lets just encode C using 110 and D using
111.
So that would be a variable length code,
the number of bits varies between 1 and
3, but it is prefix free.
And again, the reason we might want to do
this, the reason we might want to use a
variable link in coding, is to take
advantage of non-uniform frequencies of
symbols from a given alphabet.
So, let me show you a concrete example of
the benefits you can get from these kinds
of codes, on the next slide.
So let's continue with just our four
symbol alphabet A, B, C, and D.
And let's suppose we have good statistics
in our application domain, about exactly
how frequent each of these symbols are.
So in particular, let's assume we know
that A is by far the most likely symbol,
let's say 60% of the symbols are going to
be As.
Whereas 25% are Bs, 10% are Cs, and 5%
are Ds.
So, why would you know these statistics?
Well, some, in some domains, you're just
going to have a lot of expertise.
In genomics, you're going to know the
usual frequencies of As, Cs, Gs, and Ts.
For something like an mp3 file, well, you
can literally just take an intermediate
version of the file, after you've done
the analog to digital transformation, and
just count the number of occurrences of
each of the symbols.
So then you know exact frequencies and
you're good to go.
So let's compare the performance of the,
just sort of obvious fixed-length code
where you use two bits for each of the
four characters with that of the variable
length code that's also prefix free that
we mentioned on the previous slide.
And we're going to measure the
performance of these codes by looking, on
average, how many bits do you need to
encode a character?
Where the average is over the frequencies
of the four different symbols.
So for the fixed length encoding, of
course, it's two bits per symbol.
We don't even need the average, just
whatever the symbol is it uses exactly
two bits.
So, what about the variable length
encoding that's shown on the right in
pink? How many bits, on average, for an
average character given these frequencies
the differnet symbols are needed to
encode a character of the alphabet sigma.
Okay, so the correct answer is the second
one.
It's on average, 1.55 bits per character.
So what's the computation? Well, 60% of
the time, it's going to use only 1 bit.
And that's where the big savings comes
from.
1 bit is all that's needed whenever we
see an A,
and most of the characters are A's.
We don't do to bad when we see a B either
which is 25% of the time, we're only
using 2 bits for each B.
Now it is true that C's and D's were
paying the price, we're having to use 3
bits for each of those, but their aren't
very many only 10% of the time is it a C,
and only 5% of the time is it a D.
And if you added the result that's taking
the average over the simple frequencies
we get the result of 1.55.
So, this example draws our attention to a
very neat algorithmic like opportunity.
So, namely given a offer that and
frequencies of the symbols which in
general not uniform.
We now know that the obvious solution
fixed length codes need not be optimal.
We can improve upon them using variable
length.
The prefix free codes.
So the computational problem you want to
solve is which one is the best.
How do we get optimal compression? Which
variable length code gives us the minimum
average encoding length of a symbol from
this alphabet. So Huffman codes are the
solution to that problem.
We'll start developing them in the next
video.