Today, we're going to embark on the
discussion of a new algorithm design
paradigms namely that of designing and
analyzing Greedy Algorithms.
So to put this study of greedy algorithms
in a little bit of context let's just
zoom out, let's both review some of the
algorithm designs paradigms that we've
already seen as well look forward to some
that we're going to learn later on.
in this course.
So it's sort of a sad fact of life, that
in algorithm design there's no one silver
bullet, there's no magic potion that's
the cure for all your computational
problems.
So instead, the best we can do, in, in
the focus of these courses is to discuss
general techniques.
That apply to lots of different problems
that arise in lots of different domains.
So that's what I mean by algorithm design
paradigms, high level problem solving
strategies that cut across multiple
applications.
So let's look at some examples.
Back in part one, we started with the
divide and conquer algorithm design
paradigm.
A conical example of that paradigm being
the merge sort algorithm.
So remember in divide and conquer what
you do is you take your problem, you
break it into smaller sub-problems, you
solve the sub-problems recursively and
then you combine the results into a
solution to the original problem.
Like how in merge sort you recursively
sort two sub-arrays and then merge the
results to get a sorted version of the
original input array.
Another paradigm that we touched on in
part 1 although we didn't discuss it any
where near as thoroughly is that of
randomized algorithms.
So the idea that you can have codes, flip
coins that is make random choices is
inside the code itself often this leads
to simpler, more practical or more.
Elegant algorithms.
A kind of that application here is the
quick sort algorithm.
using a random pivot element.
But we also saw applications, for
example, to the design of hash functions.
So the next measure paradigm we're going
to discuss is that of Greedy Algorithms.
So these are algorithms that iteratively
make myopic decisions.
In fact, we've already seen an example of
a greedy algorithm in part 1, namely
Dijkstra's shortest path algoithm.
And then the final paradigm, we're
going to discuss in this class, is that
of dynamic programming, a very powerful
paradigm, which solves in particular, two
of the motivating questions we saw
earlier namely sequence alignment and
distributed shortest paths.
So what is a greedy algorithms anyways?
Well, to be honest, I'm not going to
offer you a formal definition, in fact,
much blood and ink has been spilled over
which algorithms precise here, greedy
algorithms, but I'll give you an informal
description.
A sort of, rule of thumb for what greedy
algorithms usually look like.
Generally speaking, what a Greedy
Algorithm does is make a sequence of
decisions.
With each decision being made myopically.
That is, it seems like a good idea at the
time.
And then you hope that everything works
out at the end.
The best way to get a feel for Greedy
Algorithms is to see examples.
And the upcoming lectures will give you a
number of them.
Algorithm.
But I want to point out we've actually
already seen an example of a greedy
algorithm in part one of this course,
mainly Dijkstra's shortest path
algorithm.
So, in what sense is Dijkstra's algorithm
a greedy algorithm? Well, if you recall
the pseudo code for Dijkstra's algorithm,
you'll recall this one main wild loop.
And the algorithm process is exactly one
new destination vertex in each iteration
of this wild loop.
So there's exactly n-1 iterations
overall.
Where N is the number of vertices.
So the algorithm only gets one shot to
compute the shortest path to a given
destination.
It never goes back and re-visits the
decision.
In that sense, the decisions are myopic,
irrevocable.
and that's the sense in which Dijkstra's
algorithm is greedy.
So let me pause for a moment to discuss
the greedy algorithm design paradigm,
generally.
Probably, this discussion will seem a
little abstract, so I recommend you
revisit this discussion on the slide.
After we've seen a few examples.
At that point, I think it will really hit
home.
So let me proceed by comparing it and
contrasting it to the per a diem we've
already studied in depth, that of divide
and conquer algorithm.
So you'll recall what you do in the
divide and conquer algorithm what you do
is you break the problem into sub
problems, so maybe to take an imput array
And you split it into 2 subarrays.
Then you solve the smaller subproblems
recursively.
And then you combine the results of the
subproblems into a solution to the
original input.
So, the Greedy paradigm is quite
different in several respects.
First, both a strength and a weakness of
the Greedy Algorithm design paradigm is
just how easy it is to apply.
So, it's often.
Quite easy to come up with plausible
greedy algorithms for a problem, even
multiple different plausible greedy
algorithms.
I think that's a point of contrast with
divide and conquer algorithms.
Often it's tricky to come up with a
plausible divide and conquer algorithm
and usually you have this eureka moment,
where you finally figure out how to
decompose the problem in the right way.
And once you have the eureka moment,
you're good to go.
So secondly, I'm happy to report that
analyzing running time of greedy
algorithms will generally be much easier
that it was with divide and conquer
algorithms.
For divide and conquer algorithms, it was
really unclear whether they were fast or
slow because we had to understand the
running time over multiple levels of
recursion.
On the one hand, problem size was getting
smaller, on the other hand the number of
sub problems was proliferating.
So we had to work hard, we developed
these powerful tools like the master
method and some other techniques for
figuring out just how fast an algorithm
like merge short runs.
Or just how fast an algorithm like
Strassen's fast matrix multiplication.
Application algorithm runs.
In contrast, with greedy algorithms,
it'll often be a one liner.
Often it'll be clear that the work is
dominated by, say, a sorting subroutine
and, of course, we all know that sorting
takes n log n time if you use a sensible
algorithm for it.
Now, the catch, and this is the third
point of comparison, is we're generally
going to have to work much harder to
understand correctness issues of greed
outcomes.
For divide and conquer algorithms we
didn't talk much about correctness, it
was generally a pretty straightforward
induction proof.
You can view the lectures on quick short
if you want an example of 1 of those
canonical inductive correctness proofs.
But the game totally changes with greedy
algorithms.
In fact, given a greedy algorithm we
often won't even have very good
intuition.
For whether or not they are correct, let
alone how to prove they're correct.
So even with a correct algorithm it's
often hard to figure out why it's
correct.
And in fact, if you remember only one
thing From all of this greedy algorithm
discussion many years from now I hope one
key thing you remember is that they're
often not correct.
Often especially if it's one that you
proposed yourself, which you're very
biased in favor of.
You will think the algorithm, the greedy
algorithm must be correct because it's so
natural.
But many of them are not.
So keep that in mind.
So to give you some immediate practice
with the ubiquitous incorrectness of
natural greedy algorithms.
Let's review a point that we already
covered in part 1 of this class
concerning Dijkstra's algorithm.
Now in part 1 you made a deal about a
justly famous algorithm Dijkstra's
shortest path algorithm is.
It runs blazingly fast and it computes
all of the shortest path.
What else do you want? Well, remember
there is an assumption when we proved the
Dykes algorithm is correct.
We assumed that every edge of the given
network has a non-negative length.
We did not allow Negative edge lengths.
And as we discussed in part one, you know
for many applications you only care about
non negative edge lengths.
But there are applications where you do
want negative edge lengths.
So let's review on this quiz why
Dijkstra's is actually incorrect despite
being so natural.
it's incorrect when edges can have
negative length.
So I've drawn in green a very simple
shortest path network with 3 edges and
I've antitated the edges with there
length.
You'll notice 1 of the edges does have a
negative length.
The edge from V to W with length -2.
So the question is consider the source
vertex s, and the destination vertex w.
And the question is, what is the shortest
path distance computed by Dykstra's
Algorithm? And you may have to go and
review, just the pseudo code in part 1,
or in, on the web, to answer that part of
the question.
And then, what is, in fact, the actual
shortest path distance, from s to w?
Where, as usual, the length of a path is
just the sum of the links of the edges
in.
In the path.
Alright, so the correct answer is d.
So let's start with the second part of
the question.
What is the actual length of a shortest
path from s to w? Where there's only 2
paths at all in the graph.
The one straight from s to w.
That has length 2.
And the one that goes via the
intermediate point v, that has length 3 +
-2 =.
The one which is shorter.
So svw is the shortest path that has
length one.
Y is Dijkstra incorrect.
Well if you go back to the pseudo code of
Dijkstra, you'll see that in the very
first iteration, it will greedily find
the closest vertex to s, in that case
this is w.
W is closer than v.
It'll greedily compute the shortest path
distance to w, knowing the information it
has right now.
And all it knows is there's this 1 hop
path from s to w.
So it'll irrevocably commute to the
shortest path distance from s to w as 2.
Never reconsidering that decision later.
So Dykstra will terminate with the
incorrect output that the shortest path
length from s to w is 2.
This doesn't contradict anything we
proved in part 1.
'Cuz we established correctness of
Dykstra.
Only under the assumption that all edge
lengths are not negative.
An assumption which is.
Violated in this particular example.
But again the takeaway point here is
that, you know, it's easy to write down a
greedy algorithm, especially if you came
up with it yourself.
You probably believe deep in your heart
that it's got to be correct all the time,
but more often than not, probably your
greedy heuristic is nothing more than a
heuristic and there will be instances on
which it does the wrong this.
So keep that in mind.
In greedy algorithm design.
So now that my conscious is clear, having
warned you about the perils of greedy
algorithm design.
Let's turn to proofs of correctness.
That is, if you have a greedy algorithm
that actually is correct, and we'll see
some notable examples in the coming
lectures.
How would you actually establish that
fact? Or if you have a greedy algorithm
and you don't know whether or not it's
correct.
How would you approach, try to understand
which one it is, whether it's correct or
not? So let me level with you.
Proving greedy algorithm is correct
frankly is sort of more art than science.
So unlike the divide and conquer paradigm
where everything was somewhat formulaic.
We had this black box ways of evaluating
recurrences, we have this So the template
for proving algorithms correct.
Really, approving correctness of greedy
algorithms takes a lot of creativity.
And it has a bit of an ad hock flavor.
That's it, as usual, to the extent that
there are recurring themes.
That is what I will spend our time
together emphasising.
So let me tell you, just a little bit
again, about very high levels.
How you might go about this, you again
might want to revisit this context af,
content after you've seen some examples
where I think it will make a lot more
sense.
So method one, is our old friend or
perhaps nemesis depending on your
disposition, namely proofs by induction.
Now for greedy algorithms remember that
they do is they sequentially make a bunch
of irrevocable decisions.
So here the induction is going to be on
the decisions made by the algorithm and
if you go back to our proof of
correctness of Dijkstra's algorithm that
in fact is exactly how we proved
Dijkstra's algorithm correct.
It was by induction on the number of
iterations and each iteration of the main
while loop we compute the shortest path
to one new destination and we always
proved that assuming all of our previous
computations.
Were correct, that's the inductive
hypothesis, then so is the computation
and the current iteration.
And so then by induction, everything the
algorithm ever does is correct.
So that's a greedy proof by induction
that a greedy algorithm can be correct,
and we might see some more examples of
those and for other algorithms in the
lectures to come.
Some of the textbooks call this method of
proof, greedy stays ahead, meaning you
always prove greedy's doing the right
thing iteration by iteration.
So a second approach to proving the
correctness of greedy algorithms, which
works in a lot of cases, is what's called
an exchange argument.
Now you haven't yet seen any examples of
exchange arguments in this class.
So I can't really tell you what they are.
But that's what we're going to proceed to
next.
I'm going to argue by an exchange
argument that a couple of different
famous greedy algorithms are, in fact,
correct.
It has a couple of different flavors.
One flavor is to approach it by
contradiction.
You assume for contradiction, that a
greedy algorithm is incorrect.
And then you show that you take an
optimal solution.
And exchange two elements of that optimal
solution and get something even better.
Which of course, contradicts the
assumption that you started with an
optimal solution.
a different flavor would be to gradually
exchange an optimal solution into the one
output by a greedy algorithm, without
making the solution any worse.
That would show that the up with the
greedy algorithm is in fact optimal and
informally that's done by an induction on
the number of exchanges required to
transform an optimal solution into yours,
and finally I've already said it once but
let me say it again, there is not a whole
lot of formula behind proving greedy
algorithm is correct.
You often have to be quite creative, you
might have to switch together aspects of
method 1 and method 2, you might have to
do something completely different.
Really, any rigorous fruit is fair gain.