This video is a segue between bad news
and good news.
The bad news which we've now discussed is
NP-Completeness; the fact that there are
computationally intractable problems out
there in the world, in fact they're
fairly ubiquitous and you're likely to
encounter them in your own project.
The good news is that NP-Completeness is
hardly a death sentence.
Indeed, our algorithmic toolbox is now
rich enough to provide many different
strategies toward coping with
NP-Completeness.
NP problems.
So, suppose you had identified a
computational problem on which on which
the success of [UNKNOWN] company rests.
May be you have spent the last several
weeks throwing the kitchen sink added/g.
All the algorithm designed for [UNKNOWN],
all the data structures, all the
primitives nothing works.
Finally you decide to try to prove the
problem is NP-Complete And you succeed.
Now you have an explanation for why your
weeks of effort have come to not.
But that doesn't change the fact that
this is the problem that governs the
success of your project.
What should you do? Well, the good news
is NP-Completeness is certainly not a
death sentence.
There are people solving, or at least
approximately solving, NP-Complete
problems all the time.
However, knowing that your problem is
NP-Complete does tell you where to set
your expectations.
You should not expect some general
Purpose, super fast algorithm, like we
have for other computational problems.
Like say, sorting or single sort shortest
paths.
Unless you're dealing with unusually
small or well structured inputs, you're
going to have to work pretty hard to
solve this problem, and also possibly
make some compromises.
[INAUDIBLE] The rest of this course is
devoted to strategies for solving or
approximately solving NP-Complete
problems.
In the rest of this video, I'll give you
an orientation for what those strategies
are, and what you can expect to come.
So as usual, I'm going to focus here on
general purpose strategies, that cut
across multiple application domains.
Means.
As usual, these general principles should
just be a starting point.
You should take them and run with them,
admitting them with whatever domain
expertise you have in this specific
problem that you need to solve.
The first strategy is to focus on
computationally tractable special cases
of an NP-Complete problem.
Relatedgee, relatedly you want to think
about what's special about your domain.
[INAUDIBLE].
About the data sets that you're working
with, and try to understand if there's
special structure which can be exploited
in your algorithm.
Let me point out that we've already done
this in a couple cases in this course.
The first example we saw concerned the
weighted independent set.
So we studied this problem on path
graphs, but the computational problem
makes perfect sense in general graphs.
The general problem is, I give you as
input an undirected graph.
Every vertex has a weight, and I want the
maximum weight subset of vertices that's
an independent set.
And remember in an independent set you
are forbidden to to take any 2 vertices
that are neighbors.
So in an independent set none of the
pairs of vertices that you've picked are
joined by an edge.
In general graphs the weighted
independent set problem is NP-Complete so
we certainly don't expect it to have an
polynomial time algorithm.
But in the special case where the graph
is a path, as we saw, there's a linear
time dynamic programming algorithm that
exactly solves the weighted independent
set.
So path graphs form a special case of the
weighted independent set problem that's
compucation retractable solvable in
polynomial or even linear time.
In fact the frontier of tractability can
be pushed well beyond path graphs.
On the homework, I ask you to think
through the case of graphs that are trees
and notice that you can still do dynamic
Programming efficiently, to compute
weighted independent sets in trees.
You can even get computationally
efficient algorithms for a broader class
of graphs, known as bounded tree-width
graphs.
So the definition of that's a little
outside the scope of this course, but you
can go even beyond trees.
So the second example follows from my
dynamic programming algorithm for the
knapsack problem.
So, we discussed that running time.
And we explained why it's exponential
time.
If the running time of our dynamic
programming napsac algorithm is n, the
number of items, times capital w, the
napsac capacity.
And because it only takes log w bits to
specify the capacity, capital w, we don't
Call that a polynomial time algorithm.
But, imagine you only have to solve a
knapsack instance where the capacity is
not too big, maybe even say the capacity,
capital W, is big O event.
And you definitely will see knapsack
instances in practice, which posses That
property, well then our dynamic
programming algorithm just runs in time o
of n squared and that's a bona fide
polynomial time algorithm for this
special case of a small knapsack
capacity.
So next let me mention a couple of
examples we're going to see in the
forthcoming videos.
The 1st 1 is going to concern the 2SAT
problem.
The 2SAT is a type of constraint
satisfaction problem.
Remember in a constraint satisfaction
problem you have a bunch of variables,
each one gets assigned a value.
So the simplest case is the Bullion case
where each value can be zero or one,
false or true.
And then you have a bunch of clauses,
which specify the permitted joint Values
of a collection of variables.
The 2 and 2 set refers to the fact that
each constraint involves the joint values
of only a pair of variables.
So a conconical constraint in a 2 set
instance is going to for 2 variables
specify 3 joint assignments that allowed.
And one that's forbidden.
So, for example, maybe it will say, oh
for variables x3 and x7, it's okay to set
them both to true.
It's okay to set them both to false.
It's okay to set 3 to true, and 7 to
false.
But it's forbidden to set 3 to false, and
7 to true.
So that's a canonical constraint in the 2
sat instance.
3 sat, it's the same thing, except the
constraints involve the join values to a
triple of variables.
And it's going to forbid 1 out of the 8
possibilities.
Now the 3 set problems a canonical MP
complete problem.
That was really singled out by Cooke and
Levin as being sufficiently expressive to
encode all problems in MP, but if each
constraint has size.
Only 2 then as we'll see the problem
becomes polynomial time solvable.
There's a couple ways of proving that.
We're going to talk about a local search
algorithm that checks whether or not
there is indeed an assignment to the
variables that similtaneously satisfies
all of the given constraints.
So the final example we'll discuss in
more detail later but just very briefly
we're going to discuss the vertex cover
problem.
This is a graph problem and a vertex
cover is just the compliment of an
independent set.
So while an independent set cannot take
two vertices from the same edge, in the
vertex cover problem you have to take at
least One vertex from every single edge,
and then what you want is you want the
vertex cover that minimizes the sum of
the vertex rates.
Yet again this is an NP-Complete problem
in general but we're going to focus on
the special case where the optimal
solution is small.
That is we're going to focus on graphs
where there's a small number of vertices.
Such that every single edge has at least
one endpoint in that small set.
And, we'll see that for that special
case, using a smart kind of exhaustive
search will actually be able to solve the
problem in polynomial time.
So, let me reiterate that these tractable
special cases are meant primarily to be
building blocks upon which you can draw
in a possibly more sophisticated approach
to your NP-complete problem.
So, just to make this a little more
concrete, let me just kind of dream up
one scenario to let you know what I'm
thinking about.
Imagine, for example, that you have a
project where, unfortunately, it's not
really 2SAT that you're confronting.
It's actually A 3SAT instance.
So you're feeling kind of bummed, 3SATs
have been complete and maybe you have
1,000 variables.
And certainly you can't do brute-force
search over 2 to 1,000 possible ways of
assigning values to your 1,000 variables.
But maybe the good news is, because you
have domain expertise because you
understand this problem instance.
You know that yeah.
There's a 1000 variables but there's
really 20 that are crucial.
You have the feeling that all of the
action basically is boiling down to how
these 20 core variables get assigned.
Well now maybe you can mix together some
brute-force search with some of these
tractable special cases, for example you
could enumerate overall 2 to the 20 ways
of assigning values to this core set of
20 variables.
To the 20 is roughly a million.
That's not so bad.
And now, what you're going to do is, for
each of these million scenarios, you
check whether there isn't a way to extend
that tentative assignment of 20 values to
the 20 variables, to the other 980
variables, so that all of the constraints
get satisfied.
The original problem is solvable, if and
only if there exists.
A way of assigning values to these 20
variables that successfully extends the
other 980.
Now, because these are the crucial
variables, and it's where all the action
is, maybe as soon as you assign all of
them 0's and 1's the residual SAT
instance is tracked.
For example maybe it just becomes a
simple 2SAT instance and then you can
solve it in polynomial time.
So this gives you a hybrid approach,
approach, brute-force search at the top
level, tractable special cases for each
guess of assignments of the 20 variables
and you're off to the races.
And I hope it's clear.
I mean this as just one possible way that
you might combine the various building
blocks for developing into a more
elaborate approach to tackling an
NP-Complete problem.
And that's generally what they take.
They take a fairly elaborate approach
because after all, they are NP-Complete,
you've got to respect them.
Expect that.
So with that digression complete, let me
mention what are the other 2 strategies
we're going to be exploring in the
lectures to come.
So, the second strategy, which is
certainly one very common in practice, is
to resort to heuristics.
That is to algorithms which are not
guaranteed [INAUDIBLE] to be correct.
We haven't really seen examples of
heuristics in the course thus far.
those of you that are alumni of part 1.
Perhaps we could classify [INAUDIBLE]
randomized minimum cut algorithm as a
heuristic.
'Cuz it did have a small failure
probability of, of failing to find, the
minimum cut.
But rather, I'm going to focus on some
examples in the upcoming lectures.
I'm going to use the [INAUDIBLE].
Knapsack problem as a case study.
And what we'll see is that our toolbox,
which contains various algorithm design
paradigms.
It's useful not just for designing
correct algorithms.
But it's also useful for designing
heuristics.
So, in particular, we'll get a pretty
good algorithm for the knapsack problem
using the Greedy Algorithm design
paradigm.
And we'll get an excellent.
Heuristic for knapsack using the dynamic
programming algorithm designed paradigm.
The final strategy is for situations
where you are unwilling to relax
correctness unwilling to consider
heuristics.
Now first one can be NP complete problem
if your hours going to be correct your
not, you don't expect to run on
polynomial time but there are still
opportunities to have algorithms that.
Well exponential time in the worst case
are smarter than naive brute-force
search.
So we have in fact already seen on
example that can be interpreted as a
implementation of the strategy, that's
for the knapsack problem.
So in the knapsack problem naive
brute-force search would just run over
all possible subsets of the items, it
would check if the subsets of items fit
in the knapsack if it does remembers the
value and then it just returns the
feasible solution with maximum value.
That has time proportional to 2^n, where
N is the number of items.
Our dynamic programming algorithm has
running time N times times capital W.
Now, of course, cap this is no better
than 2^n, if the knapsack capacity is
huge,
it is itself 2^n, But as we argued, if W
is smaller, this algorithm is going to be
faster.
And also, as you learned on the third
programming assignment, sometimes even
though W is big, dynamic programming is
going to beat the crap out of brute-force
search.
[SOUND] So I'll show you a couple of
other examples we'll talk about the
traveling salesman problem where naive
brute-force search would take roughly in
factorial time.
Where n is the number of vertices.
We'll give an alternative dynamic
programming based solution which runs in
time only 2^n which is much better than
in factorial.
The third example, which we'll cover in a
forthcoming video, we already alluded to
briefly on the last slide.
It's for the vertex cover problem.
So this is where you're given a graph.
If your vertex has a weight and you want
the minimum weight subset of vertices
that includes at least.
One endpoint from every edge.
We're going to consider the version of
the problem where you want to check
whether or not it's possible to have a
vertex cover that uses only K vertices.
Whether or not there exists K vertices
that includes one endpoint at least from
each edge.
The naiive root brute-force search will
run in time, end the K, which gets
absurd, even when K is quite small.
But we're going to show that there's a
smarter algorithm, which is still
exponential in k, but runs in time only
2^k times the size of the graph.