So I hope that pretty much all of you had
heard about the P vs.
NP question before you enrolled in this
class.
But if you haven't you can pretty much
guess what that question is.
I've defined for you both of these
classes of problems.
P is the class of problems that are
polynomial time solvable Whereas the
problems in NP have the property that, at
least given a solution, you can quickly
verify that it is indeed a correct
solution.
It's widely conjectured that P is not
equal to NP, that is, merely the ability
to efficiently verify purported
solutions, is not sufficient to
guarantee.
Polynomial time solvability.
Indeed, Edmunds, back in 1965, before we
even had the vocabulary in P.
Remember, that came along only in '71.
Edmunds, already, in '65, was essentially
conjecturing that p is not = to np.
In the form that he was conjecturing,
there's no polynomial time algorithm that
solves the traveling salesman problem.
.
But, let me emphasize.
We genuinely do not know the answer to
this question.
There is no proof of this conjecture.
.
P vs.
NP question is arguably the open question
in computer science.
It's also certainly one of the most
important and deepest open questions in
all of mathematics.
For example, in 2000 The Clay Mathematics
Institute published a list of seven
millenium prize problems.
The P vs.
NP question is one of those seven
problems.
All of these problems are extremely
difficult and extremely important.
The only one that's been solve to date is
the Poincaré conjecture, the Riemann
hypothesis is another example on that
list.
And they're not called the millennium
prize problems for nothing. If you solve
one of these mathematical problems, you
get a cash prize or $1 million.
Now, while $1 million is obviously
nothing to sneeze at, I think it sort of
understates the importance of a
mathematical question like, P vs NP.
And the advance in our knowledge that a
solution to the question would provide,I
think would be much more significant than
a price check.
So how come so many people think that P
is not equal to NP, rather than the
opposite that P = NP.
Well I think the dominant reason is a
psychological reason, mainly that if it
were the case that P = NP, than all you'd
have to do to remember is exibit.
A polynomial time algorithm for just one
NP complete problem.
And, there are tons of NP complete
problems.
And a lot of extremely smart people have
had NP complete problems that they've
really cared about, and either on purpose
or accidentally, they've been trying to
develop efficient algorithms for them.
No one has ever succeded in over a half
century of serious computational.
Work.
The second reason is sort of
philosophical.
P = NP just doesn't seem to jive with the
way the world works.
Think about, for example, when you do a
homework problem in a class like this
one, and consider three different tasks.
The first task is I give you.
A question, and I ask you to come up with
a correct solution, say a proof, of some
mathematical statement.
The second task would be just grade
somebody else's suggested proof.
Well, generally, it seems a lot harder to
actually come up with.
With a correct argument from scratch,
compared to just verifying a correct
solution provided by somebody else.
And yet P = NP would be saying that these
2 tasks have exactly the same complexity.
It's just as easy to solve homework
problems as it is to just read and verify
the correct solutions.
So I don't know about you, but it's
always seemed to me to be a lot harder to
come up with a mathematical argument from
scratch, as opposed to simply grading
somebody else's solution.
Somehow it seems to require a degree of
creativity to pluck out from this
exponentially big space of proofs, a
correct one for the statement at hand.
Yet P=NP would suggest that that
creativity.
Could be efficiently automated.
But, of course, you know, P vs.
NP being a mathematical question.
We'd really like some mathematical
evidence of which way it goes.
For example, that p is not = to np.
And here, we really know shockingly
little.
There just isn't that much concrete
evidence at this point.
That, for example, p is not = to np.
Now maybe it seems bizarre to you that
we're struggling to prove that P is not
equal to NP.
Maybe it just seems sort of obvious that
there's no way that you can always
construct proofs in time polynomial in
what you need to verify proofs.
But, the reason this is so hard to prove
mathmatically, is because of the insane
richness of the space of Polynomial time
algorithms.
And indeed it's this richness that we've
been exploiting all along in these design
and analysis of algorithms classes.
Think, for example, about matrix
multiplication.
Had I not shown you Strassen's algorithm,
I probably could have convinced you more
or less that there was no way to solve
matrix multiplication faster than cubic
time.
You just look at the definition of the
problem and it seems like you have to do
cubic work.
Yet, Strassen's algorithm and other
follow up show you can do fundamentally
better than the naive cubic running time
algorithm for matrix multiplication.
So there really are some quite counter
intuitive and hard to discover unusually
efficient algorithms with in the
landscape of polynomial time solutions.
And who's to say that there aren't some
more exotic species in this landscape of
polynomial time solvability that have yet
to be discovered, which can make any.
Roads even on NP complete problem.
At this point we really don't know, and
the very least are currently primitive
understanding of the fauna within the
complexity class p is an intimidating
obstruction to a proof that p is not
equal Equal to NP.
I should also mention that as an
interesting counterpoint to Edmond's
Conjecture in '65, was a conjecture by
Godel.
This is the same logician Kurt Godel, of
Godel's Completeness and Incompleteness
theorems.
He wrote a letter to John von Neumann in
1956, where he actually conjectured the
opposite.
That P = NP, so who knows? So I've tried
to highlight for you the most important
things that an algorithm designer and
serious programmer should know about NP
problems and NP completeness.
One thing I haven't explained which you
might be wondering about is, what on
earth does NP stand for? Anyways.
A common guess would be not polynomial,
but this is not what it stands for.
The answer's going to be a little more
obscured, and indeed it to a bit of an
anachronism; non deterministic
polynomial.
So this is referring to a different but
mathematically equivalent way to define
the complexity class NP in terms of an
abstract machine model known as
non-deterministic turning machines.
But generally for somebody's who's
thinking about algorithms it's generally
for the programmer.
I would advise against thinking about
problems in NP in terms of this original
definition with this abstract machine
model.
And I'd instead strongly encourage you to
think about the definition I gave you, in
terms of the efficient recognition, the
efficient verification of purported
solutions.
Again, they're mathematically equivalent
and I think efficient verification makes
more sense to the.
The algorithm designer.
.
Maybe you're thinking that NP is,
perhaps, not that good in somewhat
inscrutable definition for what's a super
important concept.
but it's not for lack of discussion and
effort on the community's part.
So very soon after the work of Cook and
Carp.
It was clear to everybody working in the
west on algorithms and computation, that
this was a super important concept.
And people needed to straighten out the
vocabulary asap.
So Don Knuth ran a poll amongst members
of the community.
He reported on the results in his SIGACT
news article from 1974, a Terminological
Proposal.
And NP completeness was the winner.
And that was then adopted in the landmark
book, Design and Analysis of Algorithms
by Aho, Hopcroft, and Ullman.
And that's the way it's been ever since.
There is one suggestion that was passed
over, which I find quite amusing, let me
tell you about.
The suggestion was PET. So, what is PET
an acronym for? Well, it's flexible.
So, initially, the interpretation would
be Possibly Exponential Time Problem.
Now, suppose if some day people that P is
not equal to NP, then the meaning would
change to Provably Exponential Time.
So its not the time to nit pick with the
suggestion that you could prove P not
equal to NP without actually proving an
exponential lower bound, merely a super
polynomial bound.
Lets leave objections like that aside and
ask, what would happen if P actually
turned out to be equal to NP?
Well then you could call PET, Previously
Exponential Time problems.
But of course at this point, PET is
nothing more than an amusing historical
footnote.
NP complete is the phrase that you gotta
know.