The Design and Analysis of algorithms is
the interplay between on the one hand,
general principles and on the other hand,
extantiations of those principles to
solve specific problems.
While there's no silver bullet in
algorithm design and no one technique
that solves every computational problem
that's ever going to come up, there are
general design principles which have
Proving useful over and over again over
the decade for solving problems that
arise in different application domains.
Those, of course, are the principles that
we focus on in this class.
For example in part one we studied the
Divide and Conquer Algorithm Design
Paradigm and Principles of Graph Search,
amongst others.
On the other hand, we studied specific
instantiations of these techniques.
So in Part I, we studied Divide and
Conquer and how it applies to say.
Stresses matrix multiplication, merge
short, and quick sort.
In graph search we culminated with the
rightfully famous Dijkstra's algorithm
for computing shortest paths.
This of course is useful not just because
as any card carrying computer scientist
or programmer, you want to know about
what these algorithms are and what they
do.
But it also gives us a toolbox, a suite
of four free primitives which we can
apply to our own computational problems
as a building block in some larger
program.
Part II of the course, we'll continue
this narrative.
We'll learn very general algorithm design
paradigms like Greedy algorithms, Dynamic
Programming algorithms, and many
applications including a number of
algorithms for the greatest hits
compilation.
And in this video and the next, I want to
wet your appetite for what's to come.
By plucking out two of the applications
that we'll study in detail later in the
course, specificlaly in the dynamic
programming section of hte course.
First of all, for both of these
questions, I think their importance is
self-evident.
I don't think I'll have to really discuss
why these are interesting problems.
Why in some sense.
We really need to solve these two
problems.
Secondly, these are quite tricky
computational problems.
And I would expect that most of you do
not currently know good algorithms for
these problems.
And it would be challenging to design
one.
Third, by the end of this class you will
know efficient algorithms for both of
these problems.
In fact, you'll know something much
better.
You'll know general algorithm design
techniques, which solve as a special case
these two problems, and have the
potential to solve problems coming up in
your own projects This as well.
And 1 comment before we get started on
these 2 videos, they're both at a higher
level than most of the class by which I
mean, there won't be any equations or
math, there won't be any, concrete pseudo
code and I'll be glossing over lots of
the details.
The point is just to convey the spirit of
what we're going to be studying and to
illustrate the range of applications of
the techniques that we're going to learn.
So what I want to talk about first is
distributed shortest path routing and why
it's fundamental to how the internet
works.
So let me begin with a kind of very
non-mathematical claim.
I claim that we can usefully think of the
Internet as a graph, as a collection of
vertices and a collection of.
So this is clearly an ambiguous statement
as many things I might mean as will
discuss but here's the primary
interpretations I want you to have for
this particular video.
So to specify this the vertices I intend
to be the end hosts and the routers of
the internet so machines that generate
traffic, machines that consume traffic
and machines that help traffic get from
one place.
So the edges are going to be directed and
they're meant to represent physical or
wireless connections indicating that one
machine can talk directly to another one
via either a physical link between the
two or direct wireless.
Less connection.
So it's common that you'll have edges in
both directions so that machine A can
talk to machine B directly, then also
machine B can talk directly to machine A.
But you definitely want to allow the
possibility of asymmetric Metric
communication.
So for example imagine I send an e-mail
from my Stanford accounts to one of my
old mentor's at Cornell where I did my
graduate studies.
So this piece of data this e-mail has to
somehow migrate from my machine local at
Stanford to my mentor's machine over at
Cornell.
So how does that actually happen? Well
initially there's a phase of sort of
local transportation.
So this piece of data has to get from my
local machine to a place within the
Stanford network that can talk to the
rest of the world.
Just like if I was trying to travel to
Cornell I would have to first use local
transportation to get to San Francisco
airport and only from there could I take
an airplane.
So this machine from which data can
escape from the Stanford network to the
outside world is called the gateway
router.
The Stanford gateway router passes it on
to a networks, whose job is to cross the
country.
So last I checked, the commercial
internet service provider of Stanford was
Cogent.
So they, of course, have their own
gateway router, which can talk to the
Stanford one.
Everybody's versa.
And of course these 2 nodes and the edges
between them are just this tiny, tiny,
tiny piece embedded in this massive graph
comprising all the end hosts and routers
of the Internet.
So that's the main version of a graph
that we're going to talk about in this
video, but let me just pause to mention a
couple of other.
Graphs that are related to the internet,
and quite interesting in their own right.
So, one graph that has generated an
enormous amount of interest in study is
the graph induced by the web.
So here, the vertices are going to
represent webpages, and the edges, which
is certainly directed.
Represent hyperlinks, that one webpage
points to another one.
So, for example, my homepage is one node
in this massive, massive graph, and as
you might expect, there is a link from my
homepage to the course page for this
class.
It is of course essential to use directed
edges to faithfully model the web there
is for example no directed edge from this
courses home page to my own home page at
Stanford.
So the web really exploded around in the
mid 90's, late 90's.
So for the past 15 plus years there's
been lots of research about the web
graph.
I'm sure you won't be surprised to hear
that you around the mid of the last
decade people got extremely excited about
properties of social net.
Networks, those of course can also be
fruitfully thought of as graphs.
Here the vertices are going to be people
and the lengths are going to denote
relationships.
So for example, friend relationships on
Facebook or the following relationship on
Twitter.
So notice that different social networks
may correspond to undirected or directed
graphs.
Facebook for example, corresponding to an
undirected graph, Twitter corresponding
to a directed graph.
Graph.
So let's now return to the first
interpretation I wanted to focus on.
That where the vertices are in-hosted
routers.
And it just represent direct physical or
wireless connections, indicating that 2
machines can talk directly to each other.
So going back to that graph, let's go
back to the story where I'm sending an
email to somebody at Cornell, and this
data has to somehow travel from my local
machine to some local machine.
At Cornell.
So in particular, this piece of data has
to get from the Stanford gateway router
in affect of the airport for Stanford's
network to the Cornell gateway router, so
that the landing airport over on Cornell
site.
So it's not easy to figure out exactly
what the structure of the routes between
Stanford and Cornell look like.
But one thing I can promise you is
there's not a direct physical.
Equal length between the Stanford gateway
router and the Cornell gateway router.
Any route between the two is going to
comprise multiple hops.
It will have intermediate stops.
And there's not going to be a unique such
route.
So if you have the choice between taking
one route which stops in Houston and then
Atlanta and then in Washington DC, how
would you compare that to one which stops
in Salt Lake City and Chicago? Well
hopefully your first instinct, and a
perfectly good idea is, all else being
equal, prefer the path that is in some
sense the shortest.
Now in this context, shortest could mean
many things, and it's interesting to
think about different definitions.
But for simplicity, let's just focus on
the fewest number of hops.
Equivalently, the fewest number of
intermediate stops.
Well if we want to actually execute this
idea, we clearly need an algorithm that
given a source and a destination,
computes the shortest path between the 2.
So hopefully you feel well equipped to
discuss the problem because 1 of the
highlights of part 1 of this class was
the discussion of Dijkstra's shortest
path algorithm and a blazingly fast
implementation using Heaps, that runs in
almost linear time.
We did mention one caveat when we
discussed Dijkstra's algorithm, namely
that it requires all edge links to be
non-negative, but in the context of
internet routing, almost any medge, edge
metric you'd imagine using will satisfy
this non-negativity assumption.
There is however a serious issue with
trying to apply Dijkstra's shortest path
algorithm off the shelf to solve this
distributive internet routing problem.
And the issue is caused by the just
massive distributed sale of the modern
day internet.
You know, probably back in the 1960s when
you had the 12 note ARPANET.
You could get away with running
Dijkstra's shortest path algorithm but
not in the 21st century.
It's not feasible for this Stanford
gateway router to mainly locally,
reasonably accurate model of the entire
Internet graph.
So how can we elude this issue? Is it
fundamental that because the internet is
so massive it's impossible to run any
shortest path algorithm?
Well, the ray of hope would be if we
could have a shortest path algorithm.
That admitted and distributed
implementation, whereby a node could just
interact, perhaps iteratively with its
neighbors, with the machines to which its
directly connected and yet somehow
converge to having accurate shortest
paths to all of the destinations.
So perhaps, the firs thing you'd try
would be to seek out an implementation of
Dijkstrar's algorithm, where each vertex
uses only vocal computations.
That seems hard to do.
If you look at Pseudo code of Dijkstra,
it doesn't seem like a localizable
algorithm.
So instead, what we're going to do is
different.
Shortest-path algorithm.
It's also a classic, definitely on the
greatest hits compilation.
It's called the Bellman-Ford algorithm.
So the Bellman-Ford algorithm, as you'll
see, can be thought of as a dynamic
programming algorithm and indeed it
correctly computes shortest paths using
only local Local computation.
Each vertex only communicates in rounds
with the other vertices to which it's
directly connected.
As a bonus we'll see this algorithm also
handles negative edge lengths, which of
course Dijkstra's algorithm does not.
But don't think Dijkstra's algorithm is
obsolete.
It still has faster running time in
situations we can get away with
centralized computation.
Now, what's really kind of amazing here
is that the Bellman–Ford algorithm, it
dates back to the 1950s.
So that's not just pre-internet, that's
pre-ARPANET.
So that's before the internet was even a
glimmer in anybody's eye.
And yet it really is the foundation for
modern internet routing Protocols.
Needless to say there's a lot of really
hard engineering work and further ideas
required to translate the concepts from
Bellman-Ford to actually doing routing in
the very complex modern day internet.
But yet, those protocols, at their
foundation, go all the way back the the
Bellman-Ford Algorithm.